<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fraterna correptio, or, The saints zeale against sinful altars delivered in a sermon preached on a day of humiliation for the error, heresies, &amp; schisms of our times and nations / by Z.C., minister of the word.</title>
            <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35043</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6994</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23793</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07903717</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07903717</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40347</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35043)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40347)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1204:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fraterna correptio, or, The saints zeale against sinful altars delivered in a sermon preached on a day of humiliation for the error, heresies, &amp; schisms of our times and nations / by Z.C., minister of the word.</title>
                  <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 159 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. and E.M. for Robert Gibbs,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Imprimatur, Edm. Calamy."</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Joshua XXII, 19 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40347:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fraterna Correptio:</hi> OR, THE SAINTS ZEALE AGAINST SINFUL ALTARS: Delivered in a SERMON Preached on a day of Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the <hi>Errors, Hereſies,</hi> &amp; <hi>Schiſms</hi> of our times and Nations.</p>
            <p>By Z.C. Miniſter of the Word.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Utinam talis z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lus in nobis eſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, &amp; quidem non unum Altare erectum videmus, ſed innumera.</hi> 
               <bibl>Ferus <hi>in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. in</hi> Ioſh. <hi>22</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Becauſe Ephraim hath made many Altars to ſin, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars ſhall be unto him to ſin, <bibl>
                  <hi>Hoſea 8.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>And they aroſe and took away the Altars that were in Ieruſalem. <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Chron. 30.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>We have an Altar, whereof they have no right to eate, who ſerve the Tabernacle, <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 13.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Imprimatur;</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Edm. Calamy.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> and <hi>E. M.</hi> for <hi>Robert Gibbs</hi> in Chancery lane, near Serjeants-Inne. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40347:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40347:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFUL, Mr. <hi>Daniel Andrewes,</hi> Eſquire: ALDERMAN of the Honourable City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipful,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Edications of Books being a cuſtome no leſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable then common, did engage my prefixing of your worthy name to this ſmall Treatiſe, and ſimple (I dare not ſo call it, for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter declared in it, but the management of it by the Author) Sermon: preached (in obedience to the commands of Church-Officers) ſome moneths ſince, and now
<pb facs="tcp:40347:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> publiſhed to the provoking of more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral zeale againſt ſinful Altars then our times afford. Worthy Sir, the aimes propounded to my ſelf in this preſent Dedication, are ſuch as are common to all Dedications: Firſt, to expreſſe my thankful acceptance and acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your undeſerved reſpect to me, a meere ſtranger in your frequent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance on my Miniſtery; and fervent expoſtulations with ſome in my behalf, in matters wherein I have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, and many other wayes expreſſed. Secondly, and chiefly to excite your zeal for, and engage your attendance on Gods one only Altar diſtinct from, nay, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to all falſe Altars of human ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Sir, I do not in the leaſt tax you of lukewarmneſſe, or ſuſpect your receſſion from Gods Altar: no, my ſelf, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others that miniſter to the Lord, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obſerved your conſtant attendance on the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of the Goſpel, your countenance to the Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, your complaints againſt the <hi>Errors, Hereſies,</hi> and <hi>Schiſmes</hi> of the times, with your careful turning away from ſuch as innovate new and falſe principles, and practices of Divine worſhip, muſt needs bear witneſſe that you are very fit to be
<pb facs="tcp:40347:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> one of the ten Princes of our Engliſh <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> to be delegated to expoſtulate with ſeparate brethren concerning their ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (at leaſt) building of an Altar againſt the Altar of the Lord. Sir, though I ſpeak this without flattery, yet I cannot but obſerve you obnoxious unto danger, and a fit object of the Apoſtles Caution, <hi>Let him that thinks he ſtands, take heed lest he fall:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. 10.12.</note> and that not only as you are a man ſubject to infirmity, as are your brethren: but alſo as you are eminent by your place, a Ruler in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being more ſerviceable to God whileſt you ſtand, and to Satan if you fall. We ſee <hi>Corahs</hi> rebellion and form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Altar-building-ſin drew in <hi>two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty Rulers famous in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and men of renowne.</hi> Satan well knowes he is a meane man that drawes not after him ſome Clients: and that the multitude (like Bees) follow their maſter. Hence his policie is to make the Leaders of the people, leaders of them into ſin. May I therefore be bold to commend to your reading this ſmall Treatiſe, as an antidote to tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and guard againſt all the aſſaults of Satan, by which he may labour to batter
<pb facs="tcp:40347:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> in pieces your preſent zeale to the Lords Altar. And now, Sir, I cannot paſſe over the third common aime of Dedications, wherein you may be ſerviceable to the Author; nay, to God and the ſoules of men: that is, that your eminent Name may commend this poore Sermon to publick acceptance, and your report of the words of the Lord therein ſpoke, may provoke a deſire in others the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of this ſinful Citie to read and hear it: Sir, it is worth obſervation that <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruchs</hi> roll written againſt Altar-building <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 36.13, 114, 15, 16.</note> from the mouth of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremiah;</hi> by the favour of <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iah the ſon of Gemariah the ſon of Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan,</hi> obtained an audience from all the Princes; nay, an acceſſe into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> If in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect this ſmall Tract may become a <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruchs</hi> roll; <hi>It may be they will preſent their ſupplications before the Lord, and returne every one from his evil way: for great is the anger and the furie that the Lord hath pronounced againſt this people.</hi> Sir, I will no longer trouble you, but leave it under the ſhadow of your Worſhips favour, not doubting your readineſſe to cover the infirmities of
<pb facs="tcp:40347:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> it, and its Author with your ſcarlet robe; and beg of God that it may be uſeful to your counſel and comfort in conſtant attendance on, and contentions for Gods one only Altar. This, Sir, ſhall be the daily prayer of him who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Yours to ſerve you in all Goſpel-Altar-miniſtrations, <hi>Z. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:40347:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou hast here a Sermon ſome monetths ſince preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the command of ſome in authority in the Church, on a day of Humiliation for the ſpreading Errors, Hereſies and Sciſmes of our place and times. It was then by ſome ſincere worſhippers at Gods Altar, deſired to be made more publike; but was by the Author denied, and adjudged to remaine in ſilence; yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived importunity hath reverſed that ſentence, and preſented it to thy view and cenſure; if thou haſt, as doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſons of <hi>Zion</hi> beene obſervant of what hath paſt in our Engliſh <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thou canſt not but have ſeene Church againſt
<pb facs="tcp:40347:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> Church, Miniſtery againe Miniſtery, Baptiſme againſt Baptiſme, Faſt againſt Fast, and Thanſgiving againſt Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving; ſome worſhipping God one way, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thers in a way direct contrary. Certaine it is, both cannot be the way of the Lord, one muſt be humane invention, will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ip, an Altar againſt Gods Altar, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the object of zealous reſiſtance; receive then this ſmall Tract, as that which may by the grace of God be in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure uſeful to diſcover the ſinful Altar, and direct thy duty towards it.</p>
            <p>Two things I deſire to premiſe to thee at the entrie of the work: The firſt is an anſwer to an objection, of which in the preaching of the Sermon I had not time to take notice; neither have ſince, as I might have done, inſerted it; but think convenient to note to thee in this place, It is this:</p>
            <p>If God will be worſhipped at one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Altar, how came it to paſſe that the Patriarchs and holy men of God did worſhip at various and diſtinct Altars?</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, theſe various and diſtinct Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars were uſed before God had pitched his Tabernacle and the viſible Arke of his
<pb facs="tcp:40347:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> preſence, and fixed his Name and people in a ſetled station: ſuch were the Altars of <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Patriarchs in their pilgrimage and travels: but when God had ſetled <hi>Iſrael,</hi> we read not of any ordinarily built or uſed. Hence when <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was baniſhed from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> read of his panting thirſtie deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne for the Sanctuary ſake, but not of his rearing any Altar elſewhere. It was his ſad affliction to want worſhip at Gods Altar; is would have beene his ſinne to ſet up an Altar in a ſtrange place.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Altars that at any time were erected, were able to plead extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary and immediate command from God on extraordinary and emergent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions: of this nature was <hi>Abrahams</hi> Altar in mount <hi>Moriah, and</hi> Gideons Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar called <hi>Jehovah Shalom,</hi> Judges <hi>6.24.</hi> and <hi>Davids</hi> Altar in the threſhing-floore of <hi>Araunah</hi> the Jebuſite, <hi>2 Sam. 24.25.</hi> Extraordinary precepts cannot be ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry proofs.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Theſe were temporarie and tranſient, paſſed away as ſoone as they had ſerved the ſpecial occaſion for which they were erected; ſo that God had but one permanent abiding Altar at which he was conſtantly worſhipped.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:40347:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Laſtly, Though theſe Altars were various and diſtinct in matter, yet they were one for object and forme of Divine ſervice; and if God diſpence with the matter by an immediate command, it will be no warrant ordinarily to ſet up different matter of divine worſhip.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing I would premiſe, is, by way of admonition; when thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteſt ſinful Altars, keepe ranke and order: ſtep not out of thy place and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: invade not the Miniſters Chaire, with authority to reprove, and excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate: nor yet the Magiſtrates Throne, to draw the ſword of vengeance, and drive a preſent precipitate warre againſt brethren. In thy place obſerve the ſin, mourne under it, admoniſh brethren of it, wait with patience and in peace to ſee what the Princes and Prieſts of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> will do againſt it: It is true in the text under conſideration, all <hi>Iſrael</hi> were up in armes with ſword in hand, and purpoſe in heart to reſiſt the ſinne; but obſerve <hi>Joſhuah</hi> and <hi>Phine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>has,</hi> the Princes and Prieſts of the Lord ſummon to it, and lead them in it: <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> might never ſtirre to warre till ſummoned by the ſounding alarms of the<note place="margin">Num 10.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:40347:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſilver trumpets: they roſe not to warre againſt the Altars of <hi>Baal,</hi> when <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> was addicted to a ſinful Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If God give Magiſtrates up to a ſinful indulgence of falſe Altars, it is thy duty to ſit in peace, and by ſecret mournings to reſiſt the ſinne: thy irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular inſurrection will be the ſinne of thy ſoul, and ſhame of thy profeſſion. Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader, let me therefore charge thee to performe the practices of piety with a ſpirit of peace, and to keep thy owne compaſſe in expreſſion of thy zeale to Gods Altar. I will hold thee no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but to let thee know, that if any ſhall charge this Sermon with violence and bitterneſſe, it is nothing but what is expected; and therefore was endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to be declined as farre as was conſiſtent with Miniſterial plainneſſe and zeale; and the charge being ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, will not be regarded by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, who hath taken it up for a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that our dayes denominate zeale violence, and lukewarmneſſe moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, contending for connivence at, and indulgence of poſitive ſinne, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to extend Toleration of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions ſo farre, that Schiſmes, Errors,
<pb facs="tcp:40347:7"/> and Hereſies may not only be exempted from the Magiſtrates ſword and Churches Cenſures, but even Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial reproof and private Chriſtians com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint. So commending thee to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of thy duty hereby declared; and both it and thee to the grace of a jealous God; I ſubſcribe my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine to ſerve thee at Gods ſincere and ſingle Altar,</hi> Z. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 6 <hi>line</hi> 1 woid <hi>read</hi> would, <hi>p</hi> 16 <hi>l</hi> 7 for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecton defection, <hi>p</hi> 47 <hi>l</hi> 25 <hi>for</hi> Congregrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>r</hi> Congregation, <hi>p</hi> 49 <hi>l</hi> 20 <hi>for</hi> conſent <hi>r</hi> conſent, <hi>p</hi> 50 <hi>l</hi> 4 <hi>r</hi> not ſe <hi>p</hi> 71 <hi>l</hi> 5 <hi>r</hi> as if, <hi>p</hi> 79 <hi>l</hi> 14 <hi>for Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius r Aceſius, p</hi> 80 <hi>l</hi> 5 <hi>for</hi> ſot is <hi>r</hi> it, <hi>p</hi> 105 <hi>l</hi> 13 their of <hi>r</hi> of their <hi>p</hi> 111 <hi>l</hi> 21 concernig <hi>r</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>p</hi> 120 <hi>l</hi> 10 word <hi>r</hi> wordie, <hi>p</hi> 112 <hi>l</hi> 4 immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly <hi>r</hi> immediately <hi>p</hi> 138 <hi>l</hi> 11 unifermity <hi>r</hi> uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity <hi>p</hi> 150 <hi>l ult,</hi> ſet <hi>r</hi> let.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:40347:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The INDEX. The Saints zeal againſt ſinful Altars, in which you have this Doctrine.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe building Altars beſides the Altar of Gods is a ſinne to be ſeaſonably ſeen unto by ſincere worſhippers at Gods Altar. <hi>Page 9</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>This is illuſtrated by ſhewing,</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> The ſignification of the word Altar. <hi>p. 10, to p. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Several wayes of building Altars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Gods Altar; as
<list>
                     <item>Materially. <hi>Page 20</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Objectively. <hi>Page 23</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Formally. <hi>Page 24</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Severall duties of ſincere worſhippers.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Seeing the ſinne <hi>Page 31</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Senſibly affecting themſelves with it. <hi>Page 32</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:40347:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> Seaſonable caution and counſel. <hi>Page 33</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Speedy removal of temptation. <hi>Page 34</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> Zealous reſistance. <hi>Page 36</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Doctrine is proved by ſhewing the ſinfulneſſe of the ſin in reſpect of the grounds of it.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Shameful novelty. <hi>Page 41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Swelling pride. <hi>Page 46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Self-advancement and advantage. <hi>Page 52</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Sinful acts of it.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Receding from the Lord. <hi>Page 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Renddring mans will the rule of divine worſhip. <hi>Page 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Rebellion againſt God and the Church. <hi>Page 69</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Sad effects of it.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Rending from the Church. <hi>Page 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Running God upon ſtraits. <hi>Page 79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Rendering Gods worſhip vile. <hi>Page 86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Reviving the Lords fury. <hi>Page 88</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Aggravating properties.</head>
               <item>Singularity of the ſubjects. <hi>Page 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sin agninſt ſtanding counſel. <hi>Page 92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Shuts Gods eares. <hi>Page 93</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Doctrine is applied by way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, in which you have the Characters of ſinful Altars by the concomitants of it.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Doctrines diſſonant to truth. <hi>Page 100</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:40347:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Publike aſtrological predictions. <hi>Page 103</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Separation from the Church. <hi>Page 117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Enmity to ſuch as miniſter at Gods Altar. <hi>Page 121</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Diſpenſation of divine worſhip with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due call. <hi>Page 126</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Doleful conteſts for univerſal Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Page 129</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Enquiry whether as ſincere worſhippers, we have done our duty for Gods Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar. <hi>Page 132</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Humiliation provoked by conſidering:</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> We ſin under ſtrokes of Gods fury. <hi>Page 136</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder a ſolemne Covenant. <hi>Page 138</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> It will ſubject us to ſevere judgements. <hi>Page 140</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> It is a ſymptome of Gods departure. <hi>Page 141</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The ſecond Uſe of the Point is exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to ſuch as ſeeme to build Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars.</head>
               <item>To admit enquiry, and to give to bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren a chearful account of their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Page 143</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To ſuch as have forſaken Gods Altar, to returne to it againe. <hi>Page 147</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>To ſuch as yet worſhip at Gods Altar.</head>
               <item>To ſtick to it, to stand up for it againſt all oppoſition. <hi>Page 150</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40347:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Fraterna Correptio,</hi> OR, SAINTS ZEALE Againſt Sinful Altars.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOSH. 22. the latter end of the 19. verſe.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Rebel not againſt the Lord, and rebel not againſt us, to build an Altar be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Altar of the Lord.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Incerity in the Lords Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip being alwayes ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of mixture, corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or apoſtaſie, doth inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate and bring forth a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous reſiſtance of every thing that beares
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40347:10"/> but the ſhew of innovation: This we may finde very fully manifeſted by the ten tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that had paſſed over <hi>Jordan,</hi> and poſſeſſed the promiſed land on that ſide: if we obſerve their zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous carriage (grounded but on a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and ſuſpecting jealouſie) towards their brethren of the two tribes that did abide on the other ſide of <hi>Jordan,</hi> which in this Chapter is at large declared.</p>
            <p>The Chapter is, as the Book, Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; and containes in it theſe two parts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>is Joſhuah's religious diſmiſſion of</hi> Reuben, Gad, <hi>and the half tribe of</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh, <hi>to their allotted portion of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed land:</hi> wherein after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of their paſt obedience, ready attendance on their brethren, he ſends them away with a ſolemn charge, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their obedience to Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and their conſtant adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to him, with all their heart and ſoule, unto the 9. verſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part declares the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of their return, and they are two as the moſt conſiderable.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſeq. </seg>1</label> Firſt, <hi>the work begun by them</hi> in their return to their poſſeſſion: and that is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40347:10"/> the building of a great Altar, like unto the Altar of God. A thing that might well provoke jealouſie, <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>the wiſe carriage of their <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſeq. </seg>2</label> brethren towards them, and theirs towards their brethren,</hi> on the jealous apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the work begun by them; and this is to the end of the chapter. And in their mutual carriage we may obſerve theſe things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The nine tribes and halfe <hi>obſerve it, they heard it, and heed it, v.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Prepare a power, and purpoſe a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive reſiſtance of it,</hi> if found to be as they ſuſpected, <hi>v.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Preſently diſpatch Phinehas with ten Princes to demand an account of their work,</hi> and weighty reaſons that might induce to it: as alſo to caution and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel their deſiſtance and ceſſation, <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14. who coming to them diſcharge their duties, and execute their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion theſe wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by repreſenting to them the apprehenſions of their brethren, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Altar-building, <hi>v.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by rendring the ſin vile in their ſight, if they had intended it as was feard: by aggravating the ſame by the ſin of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40347:11"/> 
               <hi>Achan</hi> and <hi>Baal-Peor,</hi> for which ſins the wounds received were yet green, <hi>v.</hi> 17, 18, and 20.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, requiring by their authority a ceſſation from ſo ſinful a work: and propounding an expedient to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived cauſe, <hi>v.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>A pathetical, religious and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly anſwer of the two tribes and the halfe,</hi> unto the meſſage received from their brethren, wherein they <hi>(though building an Altar)</hi> yet do not ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny to give their brethren an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their proceedings therein: but do</p>
            <p>Firſt, by a ſolemn appeal to God, <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt that it was not, as was ſuſpected</hi> by their brethren, to ſeparate from them, or ſet up a place for the Lords worſhip not by him commanded, or to commit ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they publiſh <hi>the very grounds and reaſons inducing, and end whereunto they built their Altar, after the faſhion of the Altar of God;</hi> (viz) that it might be a monument of their obedience, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Lord, as alſo an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to poſterity to worſhip the ſame God, at his own appointed place: ſhut
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40347:11"/> out the feared differences that might grow by the diſtance of their poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; from <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>ad</hi> 30.</p>
            <p n="5">5<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. <hi>The pleaſant departure</hi> of the meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, ſatisfied in the anſwer received, and cheared by this evidence of Gods preſence and mercy, <hi>v.</hi> 30, 31, 32.</p>
            <p n="6">6<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. <hi>The peoples denomination</hi> of their fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed Altar, according to their declared end of its erection, <hi>v.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 34.</p>
            <p>The chapter thus opened, you may ſee the words of the text to fall under the ten tribes apprehenſion of the work of the two tribes, and meſſage delivered by <hi>Phinehas,</hi> and the ten Princes, and they are an authori <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>dehortation,</hi> wherein we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe two parts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The ſuſpected ſin dehorted from:</hi> to build an Altar beſides the Altar of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The ſerious reaſons exhibited to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force it,</hi> which are two, ſetting out the nature of the ſin as it is a rebellion againſt
<list>
                  <item>God:</item>
                  <item>Us, his People.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:40347:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>If time would admit, and it were now convenient, I might from the diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted parts of the chapter infer many uſeful Concluſions and neceſſary Doctrines, but that I decline as a work more proper to the expoſition of the whole chapter, then indeed to any one thing choſen to be ſpoken to in it. I might alſo if I delighted in the mincing of the words into many parts, obſerve many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, as</p>
            <p n="1">1. The dehorters, <hi>the ten tribes by their Prieſt and Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The dehorted, <hi>the two tribes and half.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The matter from which they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted, from <hi>building an Altar beſides the Altar of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The manner of the dehortation, with the reaſons enforcing it.</p>
            <p>From theſe ſeveral parts I might infer ſo many ſeveral Concluſions, and ſpeak to them particularly: but my deſigne and deſire is, to lay before you <hi>the ſinfulneſs of the ſin of Altar-building,</hi> ſuſpected by the ten tribes to be in act in the two tribes; and therefore I ſhall deſire you to look on the words, as an abſtract of the whole carriage of the ten tribes towards
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40347:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> the two tribes on a conceived guilt: or a <hi>compendious manifestation of their ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to, and zeal for the true Worſhip of God, againſt the ſuppoſed defection of their brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the explication of the words, there is in them little or no difficulty: as for what might be ſaid to ſhew this ſin to be a rebellion againſt God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his people, I ſhall (God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) ſpeak to it in the doctrinal proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the truth to be inferred: only I ſhall deſire you to take notice, that from this hiſtory, is by the general judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Expoſitors inferred, <hi>the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates power in puniſhing hereticks and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates, and duty to preſerve uniformity of divine worſhip:</hi> nay, hereby is juſtified the making war againſt ſuch as make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from the Altar of God; <hi>Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator</hi> ſaith, <hi>It was Piety in the ten tribes, that they reſolve to make war with the two tribes for their defection from the true God. The Aſſembly of Divines</hi> ſay, <hi>Such was their zeal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Annot.</note> 
               <hi>that they had rather hazard their lives, then ſuffer Gods true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be corrupted:</hi> for God had ordained there ſhould be but one place for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip and ſervice, and but one
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40347:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Altar. The Geneva and Dutch Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiors</hi> approve the war. Not to note any thing out of Popiſh Writers, as <hi>Vatablus, Cafetan, Cornelius A Lapide, Maſius</hi> and others, who generally juſtifie the war, and with <hi>Ferus</hi> ſay, <hi>They ſent meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers to try the crime, and bring to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and were ready if the two tribes obeyed not, armis diſcernere, to decide the matter by warre;</hi> and this is neceſſary for you to take notice of, that God had ordained a ſtation for his worſhip, as well as for his people, and determined one ſpecial <hi>Altar</hi> to be erected, to which he bound his people to bring all their offerings, and by a poſitive Law prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited the erection of any other <hi>Altar,</hi> (as in <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. is to be ſeen at large) then that which was built by <hi>Moſes</hi> before the Tabernacle, and afterwards by <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> in the Temple, which, as <hi>Piſcator</hi> obſerveth, laid a neceſſity on the ten tribes to make war with the two tribes, by reaſon of which they did not conſult whether they ſhould do it or no, but the manner how to manage it: ſo that the ſtanding Ordinance of God, for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herencie to one only <hi>Altar</hi> (as the<note n="*" place="margin">Voluit Deus uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm eſſe altare in ſuo popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo: ut eſſet typus uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atoris Chriſti, tum ut eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſet nervus unitatis in Religione. <hi>Par. in loc.</hi>
               </note> ſigne of one only Mediatour, and the bond of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40347:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> unity in Religion) was by the ten tribes contended for, when they conceived their brethrens erection of another <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> in a place diſtinct from that preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the Lord to be the violation thereof; and this occaſioned the dehor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in the text, <hi>Rebell not againſt the Lord, nor rebel againſt us by building you an Altar beſides the Altar of the Lord.</hi> So that from the words thus generally conſidered and briefly opened, I ſhall commend to your Chriſtian and ſerious conſideration, this general Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Point of Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Erection of Altars beſides the Altars of God, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> is a ſin to be ſeaſonably ſeen unto by the ſincere Worſhippers of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The zealous diſcharge of this duty by <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Joſiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 18.4.23.12.</note> in the demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of <hi>Altars,</hi> beſides the <hi>Altar</hi> of God, and reducing the people to the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of worſhip, is in ſacred Records ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially mentioned as the luſtre of their religious reforming times:<note place="margin">1 Kings 15.14.</note> whileſt the neglect thereof is ſingled out and ſet up as the black butt of blemiſh to religious <hi>Aſa, Amaziah, Azariah</hi> and <hi>Jotham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 14.4.15.4, 35.</note> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Worſhippers of God.</p>
            <p>But for the more full proſecution of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40347:14"/> this truth I ſhall propound this method, to ſpeak to you by way of Illuſtration, Confirmation and Application.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by way of Illuſtration, and ſhall endeavour to open to you two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, how Altars may be ſaid to be built, beſides the Altars of God, and that even in Goſpel-dayes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, how and wherein ſincere Worſhippers of God are to act and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their duty in ſeeing to this ſin of Altar-building.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>then to ſpeak to the firſt of theſe,</hi> (viz.) <hi>how Altars may be built, even under the Goſpel, beſides the Altars of God;</hi> I ſhall deſire you to conſider the terme; <hi>Altar</hi> is in Scripture-phraſe, properly or improperly and figuratively ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>In a proper ſenſe,</hi> it ſignifies <hi>organum divini cultûs praecipuum,</hi> the chief inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the divine worſhip, ordained to be built before the Tabernacle, or in the Temple, on the which the Prieſts were to wait, that they might offer the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices the people were bound to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in that very place; of which we reade in <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. where God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40347:14"/> an <hi>Altar</hi> to be built, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to worſhip him there: even an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of his worſhip; and thus it is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally read in the Old Teſtament, for that <hi>very inſtrument of Gods worſhip:</hi> in this ſenſe the Heathens generally uſe the word and thing, and the Papiſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the ſame thing, by impoſing on us the proper and reſtrict ſenſe of the word: perſwading and practiſing the building of <hi>Altars,</hi> diſtinct places of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip for the Sacrament of the Lords Supper to be offered on, whence they call that Ordinance, <hi>the ſacrifice of the Altar.</hi> What man of but mean capacity and knowledge in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, obſerving the Lord Jeſus the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titype of both <hi>Sacrifice</hi> and <hi>Altar,</hi> ſees not their aſſertion as well as argument to be Jewiſh? (but I intending an illuſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not confutation: This having been by many of the Learned confuted,) ſhall not ſtand upon, or ſpend time to do it: only I deſire you to note, that in this proper ſenſe God under the Goſpel, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring no ſacrifices, requireth no <hi>Altar</hi> of ſtone, or brick, or the like matter to be built unto him,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.10.</note> but a ſincere and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual apprehenſion and adherence to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40347:15"/> Chriſt,<note place="margin">Habemus Altare, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delicet Chriſtum &amp; ſacro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanctum ipſius ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificium. <hi>Hun. in loc.</hi> Inep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i ſunt qui hinc alta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidea vel lignea in Templis Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirunt. <hi>Par. in Heb.</hi>
               </note> as our real and <hi>proper Altar,</hi> as wel as ſacrifice, to which every believing ſoul is <hi>privilegio,</hi> not <hi>officio,</hi> a ſpiritual Prieſt to offer prayer, praiſes, &amp;c. unto God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. So that to build material <hi>Altars</hi> of wood, ſtone and the like, muſt needs be a ſin to be ſeen unto, and withſtood, as oppoſite to Chriſt our one only Altar unto God; and that to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for Altars in this ſenſe, is ſo farre from my intent, that I with <hi>Pareus</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare them <hi>fooliſh and ſimple that ſo do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In an improper and figurative ſenſe,</hi> the word is more ſtrictly and allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally uſed by the Fathers, as <hi>Auguſtine, Optatus</hi> and others,<note place="margin">Ecce qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> qui ad convivium nupt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ale, id eſt, ad Alta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Domini aut ebrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, aut adulter, &amp;c. praeſumit accedere. Qui agnoſcens rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſuum ipſe ſe ab Altari Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſiae ſubtraxerit: ab aeterno illo &amp; coeleſti convivio excommunicari penitus non time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Aug. in Christum.</hi> De ſignis ejuſdem fractis. <hi>Aug. ad Bon. ep.</hi> 50.</note> when they do by this word denominate the Table, Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or ſeat on which the bread and the wine at the Lords Supper was placed <hi>the Altar,</hi> and ſo did vulgarly call that Ordinance <hi>the Sacrament of the Altar:</hi> the which terme of theirs the Papiſts ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king advantage or occaſion by, labour to juſtifie their Altars, &amp; impoſe it on us on
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40347:15"/> paine of hereſie to be received,<note place="margin">Ad Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile quod in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia ponitur multi ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ati acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt ad il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte quo praecurſor pro nobis introivit Ieſus nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus eorum accedere poſſunt. <hi>Aug. de ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate poenitentiae. Hom.</hi> 1.</note> much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing the Fathers above the Scriptures authority, the which their perſons and judgements were ſubject to, and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever obſerves the expreſſions of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, doth clearly ſee the oppoſition of <hi>Altar</hi> in the Temple to our <hi>Altar</hi> in Heaven, the denomination of it the <hi>wedding Supper,</hi> and in expreſſe termes ſometimes <hi>the Table,</hi> and <hi>the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> cannot but confeſſe that they did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legorically uſe the terme Altar: and in their complaints of the furious carriage of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> and <hi>Arrians,</hi> cry out of their breaking down of the boards of the <hi>Altar,</hi> and many times expreſſely of <hi>the tables,</hi> and burning the <hi>wooden board,</hi> &amp;c. for many of them at laſt, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the corruption which began to grow by the uſe of the word Altar,<note place="margin">Subſcellia thronum menſam ligneam Tabulis Eccleſiae &amp; caetera quae pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant foràs elata com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſſerunt. Atha. ep. ad ſolitariam vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am agentes: quid eſt Altare? ſedes corporis &amp; ſanguinis Chriſti.</note> where the thing was denied did more warily and improperly uſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a table, for the place of the elements: ſo that in this ſenſe we do not take the word Altar in the Doctrine: for though the Sacraments be parts of the divine
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40347:16"/> worſhip, yet I ſhall not limit and bound the word <hi>Altar</hi> to the place and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary inſtrument of their uſe: for I ſhall ſay of Tables in private places, as <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger</hi> of fixed Altars, or rather Tables ſo called. <hi>I condemn them, not being uſed to the proper end, and in a right manner.</hi> Only the conveniencie of publick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, kept in publick places, to publick ends duly preſerved, I am ſo far from reſtraining the terme Altar, to ſignifie that inſtrument we vulgar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call the Communion Table, that I ſhall with <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> confeſſe the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachreſtical uſe of it by the Fathers,<note place="margin">Dicta hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi non aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cârunt plebem, ſed potiùs illam ad Judaicos &amp; Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicos ritus impelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant: cum caecâ quâdam <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> tam à Judaeis quàm ab Ethnicis &amp; Altaria &amp; alios ritus mutuarentur. <hi>Pet. Mart. loc. Com. p.</hi> 897.</note> and acknowledge words of this nature thus uſed, may not profit the people, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally draw them to have too reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend an eſteem of Jewiſh, Heatheniſh, and (let me now ſay) Popiſh rites, the ſenſe not being underſtood in the uſe of the word.</p>
            <p>Having refuſed the <hi>proper ſenſe</hi> of the word Altar, and that reſtrict <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper figurative ſenſe,</hi> uſed in paſt ages
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40347:16"/> of the Church, we come now to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it in a <hi>ſecond improper ſignification,</hi> in which we ſhall find it uſed in Scripture, and that is in a <hi>metonymical and ſynechdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical ſenſe</hi> of the word <hi>Altar,</hi> which being but an inſtrument, (though a principal one) of the Worſhip of God under the Law, is put for the whole and every part of it: and being the ſigne of it, is often uſed to expreſſe <hi>divine Worſhip ſignified,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Unde <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the very word in the text, eſt ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium vox Hebraea, &amp; ſpeciatim atque pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificatione, &amp; generatim pro toto cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tu uſurpatur, cujus praecipua fere olim pars fuit ſacrificium. Vid. Stuch. de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificio.</note> ſo that we muſt note the <hi>Altar</hi> uſed in that ſenſe that a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man affirmes <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to be uſed, both words coming from the ſame root in the Hebrew, which ſignifies <hi>to ſacrifice,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Altars</hi> are called <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificatories,</hi> and that is for the <hi>whole Worſhip of God, of which the ſacrifice on the Altar was a chief part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word <hi>Altar</hi> thus put to expreſſe <hi>the Worſhip</hi> of God,<note place="margin">Synecdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicè po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligi, quòd cultum divinitùs inſtitutum exturbaverint, protriverint no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo idololatrico invecto. <hi>Par. in Rom.</hi> 11.3.</note> we ſhall finde in many places of the Old, and generally uſed ſo in the New Teſtament; as, 1 <hi>Kings</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:40347:17"/> 19.14. <hi>Elijah</hi> his complaint of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habs breaking down the Altars of God,</hi> which though it be by ſome underſtood literally, in its proper ſenſe; yet by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers it is expounded, that <hi>he demoliſhed the Worſhip of God,</hi> and thus generally the defect on of Gods Worſhip is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>a caſting off and forſaking the Altars of God;</hi> and reformation, <hi>a reſtoring of the ſame:</hi> and from this metonymical and ſynechdochical ſenſe, it comes to be metaphorically uſed to expreſſe the Worſhip of God under the Goſpel, wherein theſe inſtruments of Worſhip are not at all uſed, and ſo in thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies which predict the Propagation of the Goſpel, and the Worſhip of God we finde promiſed, the Temple and the Covenant of the Prieſthood to be reſtored,<note place="margin">Haec om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia quae de Altari de votis &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificiis hic dicuntur non ſunt intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cò, ſed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicè; Propheta Leviticis verbis ſignificat ea ſacra quae Evangelio Chriſti docentur. <hi>Bren. in loc.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>the Altars of God to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected,</hi> as in <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.17, 18, 21. So al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Lord promiſeth to <hi>ſet up his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar in Egypt,</hi> as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.19. and that <hi>the Egyptians ſhould offer ſacrifice unto him, v.</hi> 21. which muſt needs be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40347:17"/> of the <hi>Goſpel Worſhip,</hi> which ſhould be and hath been received in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> and not in that literal ſenſe appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by <hi>Onias</hi> the High Prieſt, and urged as the great argument to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, and indeed did (though with a cleare reluctancy of his own thoughts) prevaile with <hi>Ptolemy Philometor</hi> then King of <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Altatis autem nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne utitur ad deſignan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum velut à ſigno cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Dei: quod ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia &amp; oblationes exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citia eſſent pietatis. <hi>Calv. in loc.</hi>
               </note> to build a Temple there, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their zealous ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance to accompliſh this Prophecie as he pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, although they never proved the accompliſhment of this Prophecie in the Egyptians, <hi>ſpeaking the language of Canaan, crying to the Lord, and offering ſacrifice and oblations unto him;</hi> as alſo bringing in the Aſſyrian to joyne with them, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> as the third partie; all which are promiſed to be the concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this <hi>Altar-erection,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt confirm the former ſenſe of the word <hi>Altar</hi> as taken for the Goſpel-worſhip of God: ſo it is alſo uſed in the 56. chapter of this ſame Prophecie of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> the ſeventh verſe,<note n="*" place="margin">Calv. in loc. Brent. <hi>etiam.</hi>
               </note> where God promiſeth the <hi>ſacrifices of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40347:18"/> ſtranger to be accepted on his Altar,</hi> that is, the worſhip they ſhall do unto him through Chriſt; and thus alſo in the New Teſtament, the Worſhip of God is expreſſed by this word Altar, as, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13:10, 18. wherein he teacheth, that ſuch as are employed in the Worſhip of God, muſt be maintained by it: and that ſuch as eate of the ſacrifice offered to idols, partake in the worſhip of i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols: and ſo the word Altar muſt needs ſignifie the Worſhip of God; in <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.3. wherein our Saviour by a kinde of<note n="*" place="margin">Loquitur more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi, quando oblationes omnis generis ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciorum adhuc in uſu erant; totum verò Dei culium compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendit externum, <hi>Gualt. in loc. ſic Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Par. Aretius &amp; Dionyſ. Carth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</hi>
               </note> Jewiſh manner of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhews the neceſſity of brotherly agreement, before an approach to God in any act of divine Worſhip: and thus is Jeſus Chriſt evangelically diſpenſed, <hi>the Altar</hi> of which the ſubjects of Legal and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical diſpenſations <hi>cannot partake,</hi> Heb. 13.10. ſo that thus you ſee the word Altar, though a legal terme, yet capable of an Evangelical ſignification, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as it hath been uſed by the Profeſſors of the Goſpel, to expreſſe and ſignifie <hi>the Table,</hi> on which the bread and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40347:18"/> wine is ſet in the Lords Supper; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as it ſignifies <hi>the whole Worſhip</hi> of God; and in this ſenſe I underſtand it in the doctrine, and ſhall deſire to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in the whole diſcourſe about it: for as the Worſhip of God was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Jewes, corrupted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined by the building of any Altars, beſides the one only Altar preſcribed by the Lord: ſo under the Goſpel, all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation of principles and practices, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and above, below or beſide the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Worſhip of God in his Word, I conclude to <hi>be a rebelling against the Lord and his People, by building an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar beſides the Altar of God;</hi> for that to build a ſinful Altar beſides the Altar of God, is in the language of the Pſalmiſt to defile our ſelves <hi>with our own works, and to go a whoring after our own inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> it is to refuſe to own the object to be the Author of divine Worſhip, to be regulated by any other Law, then our own reaſon dictates, and will determines,<note place="margin">Religio ſupra ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, quae in praeceptis humanis fundata &amp; ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is pendet ac conſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> and ſo to ſet up againſt God and his people, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuperſtition and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip which the Apoſtle
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40347:19"/> dehorts the Chriſtians from, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23. and this was a ſin not only committed under the Law and Levitical Worſhip of God, but may alſo be committed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel: I, and hath been; for the Fathers in the primitive times were wont to obſerve and declare the Arrians, Novatians, Donatiſts, and other ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l hereticks diſturbing the peace of the Church, corrupting the doctrine of faith and Worſhip of God, <hi>Altare adverſus Altare erigere,</hi> to build Altars beſides the Altars of God. And that you may the better underſtand the ſame, I ſhall briefly ſhew you how Altars may be built, either materially, objectively, or formally.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Altars may be built againſt the Altars of God <hi>materially,</hi> as when <hi>any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter it innovated and introduced into the Lords Worſhip, as an eſſential part therof, which the Lord himſelf never preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed or required:</hi> and thus under the Law, the Jewes are ſadly complained of, and condemned, for the <hi>multiplying of their Altars as their Cities,</hi> J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r. 11.13. and <hi>according to the multitude of their fruit,</hi> Hoſ. 10.1. which were no other
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40347:19"/> then material organs of divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, diſtinct from that one, by which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone God would be adored: ſuch as theſe were <hi>Jeroboams</hi> two Altars at <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and ſuch as generally all the uſurping Princes of the ten tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſome of the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> did erect. And under the Goſpel we may obſerve the guilt of this ſin charged on ſuch as called themſelves true, but are branded for falſe Apoſtles, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13. in that they impoſed on the Chriſtians Circumciſion, and the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical Law as eſſential parts of Gods Worſhip, whileſt it was a matter in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating and aboliſhing, though it had formerly been eſtabliſhed: ſuch are canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſeen unto by the Church at <hi>Antioch:</hi> and conſiderately condemned by the Councel of the Church convened at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem:</hi> Acts 15.24. for that they troubled the people of God, and<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Unde argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud dialecticos ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumenta ad deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem. <hi>Lorin.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſubverted</hi> their ſouls from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per preſcribed Worſhip of God. Theſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in all his Epiſtles, to <hi>Corinth, Galatia, Epheſus, Coloſſe,</hi> or others, writes againſt, as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verterers
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40347:20"/> of the ſincere Worſhip of God received, and Innovators of their own inventions and impoſitions, therefore called a will-worſhip, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23. This innovation or rather reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the matter of Levitical Worſhip under the Goſpel, is by the Authour to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> ſet in a diametrical op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition (thorough the whole Epiſtle) <hi>to the Goſpel-Altar of God,</hi> and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be ſo ſinful, as was inconſiſtent <hi>with participation in the Chriſtians Altar,</hi> in <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.10. Thus alſo the Papiſts innovating the croſſing ceremony, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying water, the five ſacraments, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Altar, the <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to Saints, and the like matters, as eſſential parts of divine Worſhip, do clearly <hi>in the very matter build Altars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Altars of God:</hi> ſo that if the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God do offer unto God any other matter as acts of divine Worſhip, their Miniſtery will not ſanctifie their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but their innovation makes them ſubject to the guilt of <hi>Altar-building,</hi> whileſt the matter of their offering be like to the fire of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> ſtrange fire before the Lord.<note place="margin">Lev. 10.1, 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, this ſin of building Altars,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40347:20"/> beſides the Altars of the Lord, may be committed <hi>objectively,</hi> when the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry material Altar continuing, <hi>is diveried from its proper object, unto ſuch, as not being Gods, cannot be the object of divine Worſhip:</hi> as when the Temple is uſed to idolatry, the incenſe of the Lord is ſmoaking before idols, the ſacrifices of God are offered unto <hi>Baal,</hi> and the like; all which, though in themſelves the very Altar and proper matter of the Lords divine Worſhip: yet not being duly tendred to him, is the <hi>building of an Altar beſides his Altar;</hi> this ſin was committed by <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> in diverting the Temple to idolatry: and is expreſly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated to <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> when God ſhewes him the <hi>defilements of his Sanctuary, the cloud of incenſe aſcending before the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and the twenty five men worſhipping, not God, but the Sun,</hi> Ezek. 8. And of this God complaineth, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that they had defiled his Sanctuary, when they brought in their idol-ſervice into his holy place, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 5.11, 23, 38. for the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was not the Temple of the Lord, whileſt diverted to idols, any more then the temples of <hi>Apollo,</hi> or other heatheniſh gods are ſuch, when by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40347:21"/> they are diſpoſed into convenient places, for the Aſſemblies of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to worſhip in: ſo that now under the Goſpel, to give divine Worſhip to any but the true God in Chriſt, is to build Altars againſt him, and deſtroy his; for though prayer be a part of Gods Sacrifice and Worſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p, yet it is not ſo, nay, it is oppoſite thereunto, if <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> the King, the <hi>Lady Mary, Peter, Paul,</hi> or any other Saint whatſoever be the object thereof: and ſo the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, a great p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt of Gods Goſpel-Altar, ceaſeth ſo to be by the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering it unto God, as one to be appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſatisfied and reconciled by a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; and not as one already ſatisfied and appeaſed; nay, it is by the change of the object, changed in its owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and of Divine made will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Altars</hi> may be built beſides the Altars of God, <hi>formally:</hi> when the very Altar, ſacrifice, incenſe, and every matter of the Lords Worſhip is retained, and performed to the very object of divine Worſhip, the true God <hi>in a falſe manner of adminiſtration:</hi> matter miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrying in the forme is changed, as to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40347:21"/> its nature; for the axiome is true, that <hi>forma dat eſſentiam:</hi> the forme deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates the thing <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to that which it is, diſtinguiſheth it from other things, and indeed makes it to be what it is; for the matter is indeed the <hi>principium paſſivum,</hi> capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whatſoever the forme doth make it; being the <hi>principuum acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Forma eſt Principi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um activum pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quam res eſt, diſtinguitur ab aliis, denominatur, &amp; operatur.</note> and thus the ſlaying of beaſts by private men is no more then a moral act of ſlaughter, which when done by the Prieſt, is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious act of <hi>Sacrifice:</hi> and ſo under the Law, <hi>Sauls</hi> offering of beaſts in ſacrifice, is ſo far from being divine Worſhip, that it is denominated diſobedience, becauſe not done according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed forme of God,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.22, 23</note> who not only or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains the matter of his Worſhip, but alſo the manner and forme thereof: and in this ſenſe the ſin of <hi>Corah</hi> and his company may be ſaid to be the <hi>erecting of an Altar beſides the Lords Altar,</hi> when by the gathering of a <hi>guedah</hi> or Congregation out of the Congregation, they did ſeparate from the Church of God, and on the pretence of Piety cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40347:22"/> up all the people as holy, <hi>invade the Miniſterial deſpenſation of God without due forme and order:</hi> whereby they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked the Lord to vindicate the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal adminiſtration of his Ordinances by the ſeverity of his judgements on them,<note place="margin">Numb. 16 Pſal. 106.16, 17.</note> and by his Statute concerning their cenſers, that they ſhould be plates of memorial, that no ſtranger, not of the ſeed of <hi>Aaron</hi> formally called, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to celebrate divine Worſhip: and their ſin the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> in his general Epiſtle notes, to have been committed under the Goſpel; and in all the action we finde no change of the matter, but only the miſcarriage of the manner in a ſeparate way, by ſuch as were not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Miniſters. An act like unto this was that of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzahs,</hi> in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.8. in lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hold upon the Ark of God not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally called: <hi>the danger of religions ruine will be no warrant for men not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally called to it, miniſterially to ſupport and ſave it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great aggravation of <hi>Jeroboams</hi> ſin and evidence of his <hi>Altars to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Altar of God,</hi> was his expulſion of ſuch as were formally called to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate divine Worſhip, and eſtabliſhing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40347:22"/> of his uſurped Magiſtracy, by an uſurped Miniſtery, (<hi>for he that would, made himſelf a Prieſt,</hi> to adminiſter ſacred actions contrary to Gods ſtanding Law, and ſignal ſeverity on <hi>Corah</hi> and his company for this ſin) as we at large ſee in 2 <hi>Coron.</hi> 13.9, 10. whileſt <hi>Abijah</hi> declareth <hi>Judah</hi> to retain the truth of Gods Worſhip and Altar, not only in the matter and object, but the forme and manner thereof by the <hi>ſtanding Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of God.</hi> And as we finde the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the forme under the Law in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred diſpenſations, to be <hi>principium tranſmutationis,</hi> the changing of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Ordinance of God, from holy to profane: ſo alſo we ſhall ſee it to be under the Goſpel; for though ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration in the Name of Jeſus be in it ſelf a ſacred action, yet when diſorderly and precipitately without<note n="*" place="margin">Legitima autem no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis Dei &amp; Chriſti in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocatio eſt, quae ſide diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur, nec excedit voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis metas. <hi>Calv. in loc.</hi>
               </note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal authority uſed by the <hi>Exorciſts,</hi> it will provoke the devil himſelf to juſtifie the power of Jeſus and <hi>Paul,</hi> but to torment theſe u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping Intruders, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.13, 14, 15, 16. The neglect of the formal admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Lords Supper in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40347:23"/> Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> will engage a ſincere <hi>Paul</hi> to affirm poſitively, it is<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.20. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat eos tunc edere Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Dominicam quia il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legitimè edere, ſit non edere. <hi>Par. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>not to eate the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> at all; for the forme deſtroyed the entity which muſt be reſtored by a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal returne to the firſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred inſtitution: and I cannot but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the care and paines taken by the Authour of the Epiſtle to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,</hi> in aſſerting the <hi>formal inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> and exerciſe of the Lord Jeſus in the work of the High Prieſt towards God, that he might convince the Jews that he was no uſurping Impoſtor, but really and formally the High Prieſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, eſpecially in the fifth chapter of the Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>So that hereby we may ſee that men may provoke God <hi>by their own inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and go a whoring after their <hi>own wayes,</hi> in not only adulterating the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> but alſo the very <hi>manner</hi> of the Lords worſhip: and this muſt needs be a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſin in Altar-building, to make Gods Altar to ſtand againſt it ſelf, nay, whileſt it ſeemes to be (and ſo is more apt to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce,) what indeed for want of <hi>miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial authority,</hi> and <hi>formal diſpenſation</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:40347:23"/> it is not: thus the Aſſemblies of the <hi>Novatians, Donatiſts</hi> and <hi>Arrians,</hi> though uſing Word, Prayer and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, were denominated <hi>builders of Altars:</hi> for that action, which is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred in the hands of a Miniſter, is but common in the hands of private men: the Lords Supper duely adminiſtred by a lawful Miniſter thereun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ordained, will be but at the beſt a <hi>Corinthian</hi> love-feaſt in a <hi>John of Leydens hand:</hi> and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme a ſacred ſigne and ſealing part of Gods Worſhip, when adminiſtred by a lawful Miniſter in the Aſſemblies of Gods people, will be (to uſe, but not to own the Anabaptiſts phraſe) but <hi>baby-waſhing by a Midwife,</hi> and but meer waſhing of the body <hi>by the loweſt of the people,</hi> renouncing or never receiving Miniſterial authority: preaching of the Word, the great part of Gods publick worſhip in the mouth of a Miniſter, will be but the ſimple ſpeaking of things as good or true, but not as engaged by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to enforce with authority by a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man. Having thus given you to ſee what I underſtand by Altars, and the different wayes whereby they may be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40347:24"/> built, beſides the Altar of God. I ſhall cloſe this firſt part of the illuſtration of the Point, with this ſad obſervation which I cannot be ſilent in, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of our nature and times is apt to carry us from one extream to another.</hi> Whileſt we are reforming material in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations,<note place="margin">As the learned <hi>Didoclavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, alide Cather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> did denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the late corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> we run after a ſuperſtitions manner of adminiſtration of ſacred worſhip; and though we lately, and yet loudly cried for the purity of Gods Altar, yet we are apt to deſtroy the power, by taking away the Prieſtly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial authority thereof, which muſt concur to make actions ſacred, and parts of divine worſhip.</p>
            <p>I come now in the next place to ſhew you what muſt be done by ſincere wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of God, that they may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their duty of <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing to this ſin of Altar-building,</hi> in the reſolution of which I ſhall dictate ſome few directions from the precedent in this chapter; wherein if we obſerve the carriage of the ten tribes on this conceived act of <hi>Altar-building,</hi> we ſhall finde theſe duties to be done by ſuch as would ſee to this ſin.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>they muſt ſatisfie themſelves of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40347:24"/> the certainty of ſuch an act to be in agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> they muſt take cognizance of the fact before they condemn it: they muſt have eares and eyes open to attend to reports, and obſerve actions; and hearts rightly acted to apprehend and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the nature of ſuch things as they hear and ſee; they muſt not ſhut their eyes at all affairs abroad becauſe of their own liberty at home: nor live at peace themſelves, and leave all others to ſerve God as they liſt; but knowing that there is but one God, and one Altar or way of worſhip, they muſt ſee whether all that call themſelves by the Name of the <hi>God of Jacob,</hi> do wait on him at that one <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> or erect any other to any ſinful end. Thus we ſhall finde the ten tribes carrie towards their brethren; they are ſo farre from condemning complaints of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and contending for the liberty of the men, that they take notice of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and are ready to fire their bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons on a bare report: ſee, <hi>v.</hi> 11, 12, <hi>they heard ſay,</hi> and begin to ſtir; yet they run not raſhly upon a bare report to ruine their brethren, but ſend choſen men to require and receive an account of the work in hand, by them ſuſpected to be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40347:25"/> 
               <hi>ſinful Altar-building:</hi> who returning ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in themſelves, do alſo ſatisfie the Congregation; ſo that the firſt thing to be done, is to ſearch out the certainty of the thing: that by ſinful ſilence occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by non-obſervance, they indulge not <hi>building Altars beſides the Altars of God,</hi> on the one hand, or on the other run raſhly on the ruine of their brethren, condemning without conviction, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the innocent in a juſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they muſt <hi>ſenſibly affect themſelves with the nature of the ſin and the ſad aggravations thereof.</hi> The hiding of ſin under the tongue ſhews that it is ſweet in the mouth,<note place="margin">Job. 20.12 13.</note> and reſolved to be kept and ſpared. Sins aggravation is the ſoules exaſperation againſt it, wherein it is extenuated the heart is not affected with ſorrow for it, or zeal againſt it: <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſeeing to the reformation of the Sabbath of the Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ne.</hi> 13.17</note> heigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ens the ſin to his own and the peoples ſenſe; <hi>What evil is it that you do? did not your fathers thus? did not God bring all this evil for this ſin? will ye yet bring the wrath of God on us?</hi> So the ſincere worſhippers of God in the text, contending againſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40347:25"/> the ſuſpitious act aggravate it very much, calling it <hi>a treſpaſſe committed, a turning away from the Lord, rebellion againſt God and their brethren</hi> conſidering it to be a provocation of divine wrath,<note place="margin">Verſ. 16, 17, 18. of this chap.</note> parallelling it with <hi>Achans ſinne;</hi> and making it the more grievous, becauſe of the hand of God yet on them for the late ſinne of <hi>Baal-peor;</hi> in reſiſting the ſinne of <hi>Altar-building;</hi> we muſt then not abate, but aggravate the ſinful nature thereof; for aggravations extract ſorrow and emulate zeal.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>ſeaſonably caution, and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly counſel the deſiſtance of ſo ſinful a deſigne;</hi> all meanes muſt be uſed to cure the wound before it be pronounced <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medicabile vulnus enſe recidendum,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable: for although to ſuffer obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy againſt advice, were ſinful indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; yet to ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke precipitately without ſolid conviction, and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous counſel to deſiſt, is no better then Papal tyranny. Sincere worſhippers muſt in contending for Gods Altar, be actuated by Gods counſel, to give <hi>firſt and ſecond admonition</hi> before the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of <hi>an heretick,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3.10.</note> and imitate the pattern of Gods patience, in warning
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40347:26"/> and wooing before they war: ſin perſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in againſt counſels and cautions, pleads the equity and neceſſity of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and ſeverity: whileſt the purſuit of iniquity without theſe preventing means bears the complexion of paſſionate, and prejudged executions: and therefore the ten tribes though aſſembled with ſword in hand, and purpoſe in heart to correct this ſuppoſed ſinne: check their courage, and command a ſtay to their proceedings, till they counſel their brethrens ceaſing from ſo ſinful a deſigne by the embaſſie of <hi>Phinebas,</hi> and his aſſociates.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>ſpeedily accommodate our brethren with a removal of what ariſeth from our ſelves as an accidental tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ſinne, and may ſafely be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:</hi> ſelf-intereſt is alwayes a ſad ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer of ſincere contentions for Gods worſhip: when ſelf-denial ſets Gods Altar above all our own enjoyments, and commands a condeſcenſion of the loweſt and hardeſt ſuffering tearms that may anticipate poſitive and direct ſinne: Sincere worſhippers muſt have a <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit, to become all things to all men, that all men may in ſincerity obey the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40347:26"/> Goſpel of Chriſt; who will rather <hi>never eat fleſh</hi> then any ſhall thence take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>to refuſe or recede from Chriſtianity:</hi> who will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather labour with his hands then that the burthen of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſhall make it be diſtaſteful (though he have power to expect, if not exact maintenance) and like unto the tenne Tribes in the Text, who will rather though to the diminution of their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready divided inheritances, admit ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diviſion, and allow<note n="*" place="margin">Credibile eſt ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſque tribus non ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis laxe habitaviſſe, cum tot paſſim eſſent Cananaei; &amp; tamen gentem ob hominum multitudinem à r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniaria copioſiſſima ſedibus atque poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus recipere; ſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que urbes atque a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gros quae illis attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt detrahere malunt; quam ut adeo tradita religionis jura mutari aut pollui ab illis paucis tribubus ſinant. <hi>Maſ. in Joſ.</hi> 22.19.</note> a portion for their brethren, then that they ſhall divide from the Altar of God: Knowing that it is better for them to admit poverty then profaneneſſe. Groundleſſe ſcrupuloſity ſometimes doth (as in the caſe in the Text it was conjectured to have done) engage men to ſchiſme and ſeparation from the ſincere worſhip of God; therefore wherein the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended cauſe, though clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accidental, may with ſome diſadvantages as to our own enjoyments be removed; the care of ſuch
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40347:27"/> as contend for the conſervation of the Altars of God, muſt be to ſee it done, and condeſcend to the ſame: that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may ſhew to the ſilencing of the ſinners, it is ſimple purity of Gods worſhip they purſue.</p>
            <p>The fifth and laſt duty, inferred from this very ſtory, to be done by ſincere worſhippers of God in their contending for the Altars of God, is <hi>zealouſly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſist the ſinne of Altar-building:</hi> this is the part of their duty the loud cries of general liberty amongſt us doth decrie: yet it muſt be done:<note n="*" place="margin">Non du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium eſt quin ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto zelo excanduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint: non omnibus quidem datus gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius in manumſed Pro ſua quiſque vocatione et officio viriliter &amp; conſtanter ſtudeat purum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis ſtatum contra omnescor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptelas. <hi>Calv. in text.</hi>
               </note> every one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bound in his proper place, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his capacity, to approve themſelves true attendants on Gods Altar and Sanctuary, by withſtanding ſinne in the <hi>genus</hi> of it, and ſo in every particular <hi>ſpecies,</hi> eminently attempting to reſtraine ſchiſme from the Church, and ſad apoſtaſies from the worſhip of God. Although we do not ſee, or ſay that ſtrangers to the God, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were to be by force com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to become proſelytes to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and to worſhip at their Altar: yet what is clearer in all the ſtory of the Church then that they were to be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40347:27"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Judaei neminem proſelytum faciebant donabant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e jure ſuae gentis niſi prius ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe circumcidiſſet, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> recepiſſet &amp; eorum ſacrificiis communicaſſet. <hi>Pet. Mart. loc. Com. p.</hi> 204.</note> reſtrained from worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping at any other Altar, or any other god in the midſt of them: how much more cleare is it that all defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or backſliding from the worſhip and Altar of God by ſuch as were joyned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the viſible adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Covenant, was with a Spirit of zeal and a ſtrong hand to be reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Is not this in this very ſtory, ſo very clear, that he that runs may read? See we not the people of the ten Tribes general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſembled with power in hand, and purpoſe in heart to impede the ſuſpected ſinne, and ſo to keep in due order of attendance on Gods Altar? Is it not to this end that God hath inveſted his Church with authority, and cenſures, and requires the due execution thereof, that by fear men may be forced from ſinne? Is not the cutting off the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of Gods Church, rejection of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, caſting off and delivering up to Satan for the buffetting of the fleſh, the very act of this reſiſtance? Was it not the diſcharge of this duty that emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Apoſtles in their dayes,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.</note> and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40347:28"/> faithful Miniſters of the Goſpel, by the Authority of Chriſt to withſtand the falſe Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.12. Tit. 3.10</note> and ſeducing teachers of their times, as <hi>ſinful Altar-builders,</hi> that this lies as a duty on the authority of the Church is generally granted by all, even by ſuch as deny the ſame to be a duty in the Magiſtrate, which at this time is not my part or purpoſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, having been done by more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, and that very fully; that onely which I would dictate is, that in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral every profeſſed ſincere worſhipper of God, is to approve himſelf ſuch, not onely by cautionating againſt, or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelling from, but alſo in his place, and according to his capacity, in contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the ſinne of Altar-building, as private Chriſtians by friendly objur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and diſcountenancing the ſame, even by drawing from communion and otherwiſe, when duly called: Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Church by reproving, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning and cenſuring, nay if thereunto called, defending the place of Gods worſhip againſt their entrance into the ſame, to correct their ſin, as did <hi>Alexander</hi> that famous Biſhop of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> and undergoing not onely
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40347:28"/> cenſures of bitterneſſe and violence, but even baniſhments and ſaddeſt ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as did <hi>Athanaſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> in withſtanding the <hi>Arrians:</hi> and when I conſider Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates waiting on the Altar of God by the fulneſſe of their power, and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their authority on the ſons of men, to be in the ſitteſt capacity to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage to the purpoſe this reſiſtance. I cannot ſee (whatever others ſay to the contrary) how to exempt them from the approving themſelves ſincere worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers at Gods Altar, by the faithful and zealous diſcharge of this duty.</p>
            <p>Thus then I have done with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing to be illuſtrated, and have ſhewed you what duties he on the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere worſhippers of God in ſeeing to the ſin of Altar-building, and you ſee they muſt, 1. See it. 2. Be ſenſibly affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it. 3. Speedily cautionate from it. 4. Seaſonably remove acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental occaſions as farre as may be. 5. Zealouſly reſiſt when other means will not availe, that ſo they may not ſhare in their guilt. I now come to the confirmation of the Point thus illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by giving the reaſons of it.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:40347:29"/>
            <p>The reaſons, why the building of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars beſides the Altar of God is to be ſo ſeaſonably ſeene unto by the ſincere wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of God, I ſhall briefly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend under one general head, and that is this:</p>
            <p>To <hi>build Altars beſides the Altar of God is a ſinne exceeding ſinful:</hi> it is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to emulate a ſanctified heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, to aſſert it ſimply to be a ſin, though of the loweſt order; for ſaving grace doth militate againſt ſinne as ſuch, not as it is more or leſſe grievous: yet how much more fervently and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will it bend it ſelf againſt ſinne, as it appears aggravated, vile, and exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinneful, more eminently and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately diſhonouring God, provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king fury, ſcandalizing religion, and ſadly dividing the Churches of God? of which nature, to the emulating of zeal, and engaging the ſtrength of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere worſhippers of God againſt it, I ſhall labour to let the people of God ſee this ſinne of Altar-building to be; and that in the conſideration of the grounds, actings, effects, and ſad aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations thereof.</p>
            <p>F rſt, Altar-building beſides the Altar
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40347:29"/> of God, will appeare a ſin exceeding ſinful, if we conſider the <hi>ſinneful grounds</hi> from whence it ſprings and ariſeth; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others we may ſpecially take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of theſe three common cauſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>ſhameful novelty;</hi> that frame <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ground </seg>1</label> of ſpirit which for its vileneſſe is noted to be the effect of idleneſſe and want of ſerious imployment which might ſix<note n="*" place="margin">Variam dant otia mentem.</note> the ſoul; this is that frame of Spirit which renders a man weary of every thing though in it ſelf never ſo good: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men become <hi>Athenians</hi> to give up themſelves to things as they are <hi>new,</hi> rather then as they <hi>are good,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine <hi>as new,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 17.19</note> and ſo ſuitable to their curioſities rather then <hi>as true</hi> and ſaving to their ſouls; the which although noted as an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching, yet is taxed as an evidence of their vanity who minded nothing elſe but novelties, which might be vanities according to the Greek proverb <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties commonly are vanities. This is that ſhameful ſinne which brings a diſtaſte on the moſt pleaſont object<note n="*" place="margin">Apparet etiam quare tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>topere no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vae res placeant, quoniam mens cum primum quippiam nobile ac p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aeſtans affert ſe contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plandum, acriter &amp; attente ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quo cognito de ſtudio remittit, ideo volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptas defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit: verum ſi priori objecto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponatur, denuo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligentia contendit ſtudium ea contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plando, &amp; voluptas redit, atque hoc pacto ſemper rebus novis obiecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>Pet. Mart. loc. com. p.</hi> 330.</note>, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth affection on that which is more
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40347:30"/> baſe: a diſpoſition more fit for babes and children, then men of diſcretion, who ſhould embrace by reaſon: this novelty is the mother of ſedition in States and Republicks, which a wiſe <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curgus</hi> will labour to anticipate by his perpetual abſence from his <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> ſubjects engaged to conſtancy of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence till his return: and chiefeſt polliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, by aſſenting to <hi>Plato</hi> his directions, and ſeeing that <hi>ne quid in rebus ad reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionem attinentibus innovetur,</hi> that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties in religion be not admitted. In a word, ſuch is the vileneſſe of this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous temper, that Satan cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure his wayes and doctrines to be charged with novelty, which he therfore cloaks with the plea, and brings in with the loud cry of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> whileſt he makes the truths, and wayes of God diſtaſtful with the charge of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus</hi> caſt the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> out of the Church as new found figments of late Writers. <hi>Euſeb. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 29.</note> 
               <hi>novelty,</hi> which need; no clearer proof then the Papiſts contention for their ſhameful ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities, and horrid innovations with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40347:30"/> the pretence of antiquity, whileſt their common captious calumniating queſtion againſt the true Churches doctrine and worſhip of God is, <hi>Where was Proteſtant religion before</hi> Luthers <hi>time?</hi> this ſinful frame of ſpirit, this ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful inconſtancy of the ſoule in its ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and wearineſſe of any thing, though in it ſelf never ſo good, when a little old is clearly in Scripture dictated to be the cauſe or reaſon of building Altars againſt the Altars of God. God expreſſely char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it on the <hi>Jews,</hi> that being more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous then other Nations they had changed their glory into that which would not profit, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.11. When thou didſt nothing elſe but build other Altars unto Idol-gods: which in this very regard, to note this very ground of following them, by forſaking God, are called <hi>new gods, that came newly up, whom their fathers feared not.</hi> As in <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.17. And when God calls them off from this ſinne of Altar-building, we may finde him correcting their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty, as that which led them into the ſin, by calling on them to enquire after the good way, and <hi>the old,</hi> and walk therein, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.16. and many times he
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40347:31"/> pleads his antiquity as a Creator, and as their Redeemer to confirm againſt Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh idolatry, and curb their novelty in acting this ſinne: thus and to this end is God oppoſed to idols with expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating tearmes: <hi>Have ye not heard? hath it not beene told you from the beginning?</hi> have you not underſtood <hi>from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the earth,</hi> that I as <hi>the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Creator of all things,</hi> am the ſole and onely object of Altar-worſhip?<note n="*" place="margin">Non habetis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitium Deum, ſed eum ipſum qui <hi>Abrahamo, Moſi,</hi> patribuſque ab initio patefecit, &amp; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te non parva hinc confirmatio accedit, quod vetuſtas doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae nobis conſtat quae per tot ſecula inter fideles continuata eſt. <hi>Calv. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. from <hi>ver.</hi> 18. to the end of <hi>chap.</hi> 41. at large to be ſeen; and ſo alſo we ſhall finde the ſin of Goſpel-Altar-building in turning away from the doctrine and worſhip of the Goſpel to be expreſſely grounded on, and flowing from this ſhameful novellous property: the Apoſtle uſeth no enigmatical tearmes when he makes this ſinful, baſe diſpoſition, and its ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects the argument to excite faithful Miniſters of Chriſt to approve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſincere worſhippers of God, by zealous and diligent preaching, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon; for the time will
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40347:31"/> come when men <hi>having itching eares,</hi> given wholly to novelty, (not to be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for their delicacy) will turne from the Altar of God not <hi>enduring ſound Doctrine,</hi> but will ſet up new Altars according to their own luſts, by the <hi>heap of teachers gotten</hi> to themſelves,<note n="*" place="margin">Cauſam tanti mali dum vult aſſignare, eleganti Metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra utitur, qua ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat tam delicatis auribus mundum fore, tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> rerum novarum perperam cupidis, ut varios ſibi magiſtros accumulet atque ad nova i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentidem figmenta circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur. <hi>Calv. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3, 4. So that ſhameful novelty to be the ground of this grand iniquity we ſee clearly and poſitively aſſerted in Scripture; to which we might adde the experimented diſpoſition of ſuch in all ages of the Church of God, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining the ſincere Word and worſhip of the Lord, and dividing from the ſociety of ſincere worſhippers, have by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſtes of found doctrines, and inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in their own oppoſed principles, and practices embracing and with zeale advancing for truth to day, that which with no leſſe zeale ſhall be condemned for errour to morrow: increaſing to themſelves teachers, and deſirous to heare every one ſpeak, though they will know none to <hi>be over them in the Lord:</hi> being (in a word apt) <hi>to try all things,</hi> but never to determine any thing, <hi>to hold it faſt as good:</hi> approve themſelves men acted by no other principle then novelty:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40347:32"/> but thus much may ſuffice (I hope) to convince, that Altar-buildings many times comes from this very ground ſhameful, ſinful, childiſh novelty, which as you heard is ſo vile, as to make a people to decline their God long, nay, alwayes enjoyed and approved merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and gracious to them, to imbrace thoſe novellous vanities which are but momentany, and with which they were not acquainted: but I muſt paſſe to the conſideration of the ſecond ground, or cauſe of Altar-building, which we ſhall finde no leſſe ſinful to the aggravation of this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ground </seg>2</label> The ſecond ground of Altar-building is <hi>ſwelling pride,</hi> that diabolical diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition that put the evil Angels on an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of their Creator, from their very beginning to build their own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: that high frame of ſpirit which admits no peeres, much leſſe ſuperiours: that boundleſſe property that cannot endure to be preſcribed by any rules, or confined within any banks: which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing its own inventions will contend with men, nay, as much as may be with their ſovereigne Creatour for Maſtery, to which nothing but ſingularity and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40347:32"/> ſuperiority can give ſatisfaction. In a word, that curſed principle, which ſucks nouriſhment from Gods greateſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and moſt gracious favours; and when ſtrengthened thereby, manageth a reſiſtance of his ſacred pleaſures, and ſtruggles to ſeat it ſelf in the divine chair, much more eaſily to preſcribe the form and bounds of that obedience which it will yield; this is a root ſo notoriouſly vile, that none will own it but where it reignes be ready to excuſe, I and with ſeeeming zeal condemne it: its evil na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſo fully known as well by the light of nature and long experience, as by the law of God, that to enlarge on the diſcovery of its vileneſſe were almoſt loſt labour: yet from this odious and abominable root doth ſpring this curſed branch of Altar-building: which muſt needs ſavour of that ſeed it doth extract: this was the principle that put forward <hi>Corah and his company</hi> to gather a <hi>Gnedah</hi> out of a <hi>Gnedah, a Congregation out of a Congregration,</hi> and to build an Altar againſt the Altar of God, by declining, nay, diverting the formal adminiſtration of divine worſhip in the hand of <hi>Aaron;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 16.</note> for we ſee not that they went about
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40347:33"/> to renounce the material Altar of God: who can obſerve their ſtubborn refuſal to come, when <hi>Moſes</hi> called, with a proud, though unjuſt recrimination on <hi>Moſes,</hi> their puffed up ſpirits expreſſed in their plea of univerſal holineſſe, with which they being too highly affected durſt argue againſt order and priority, and think al above them to <hi>take too much upon them:</hi> who can conſider the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Gods judgement, and their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers made ſignes and monuments of caution to humility for future genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and not be clearly convinced that <hi>pride was the root of all their evil of ſinne,</hi> which cauſed their ſorrow? <hi>Moſes</hi> charged this ſin of Altar-building in the declining of the Altar of the true God, and ſetting up Altars to their new gods to be the overflowing effect of the <hi>Jews ſwelling pride,</hi> when he digitates the time of this abomination to be when <hi>Jeſuron was waxed fat:</hi> and expreſſely notes to have been the cauſe thereof, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.15, 16, 17. And as this evil diſpoſition drew ſtrength from God increaſing mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in after-ages, ſo alſo did increaſe this ſinne of Altar-building cauſing the ſad complaints of the Prophets in <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.1.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40347:33"/> 
               <hi>according to the multitude of fruit they have increaſed their Altars.</hi> Through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Old Teſtament, whenſoever God by his ſervants reproves this ſin, he aggravates the ſame by the expr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their pride, as in <hi>Iſ.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. from the 2. to the 7. verſe. And in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we finde Apoſtates, Seducers, Innovators in to the Lords Word and Worſhip, ſtigmatized with this brand of pride; the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing ſuch as labour to draw aſide ſilly women, and to ſet up their own Altar, ſaith of them among other properties that apt them for this work, that they are <hi>proud, heady, high-minded,</hi> in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 4. and in his firſt Epiſtle, the ſixth chapter, the third and fourth verſes, notes, that ſuch as teach oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rwiſe, and conſent not to wholeſome doctrine, are <hi>puft up, knowing nothing,</hi> and that he may clearly, evidence that this proud proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie produceth a declining of the Altar of God, and building others, he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to anticipate this ſad effect by a neceſſary caution concerning the cauſe, in ſuch as take the charge of the Churches of God,<note n="*" place="margin">Non <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hibet apoſtolus, quales e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>humeni. <hi>Calv.</hi>
               </note> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. where he adviſeth, <hi>that a Biſhop be not a novice,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:40347:34"/> ungrounded in the principles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and that for this very cauſe, <hi>leſt he be proud, and ſo fall into the ſnare of the devil.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> in his ſe-ſecond Epiſtle, the ſecond chapter, ſets out ſeducers with the ſame characters, <hi>They ſpeak evil of dignities, and of what they know not, and ſpeak great ſwelling words of vanity.</hi> And <hi>Jude</hi> omits not this propertie, when he aſſerts them <hi>to deſpiſe Governments, and to ſpeak evil of dignities,</hi> to ſpeak proud things; and analogically aſſerts their way to be the <hi>gain-ſaying of Corah.</hi> But to cloſe up what might be more largely ſpoken to evidence this graceleſſe propertie, to be the ground of this grand iniquity, that might appear grievous in the eyes of the ſincerely gracious; I will only adde this one general obſervation, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the ſin of Altar-buildng never was ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently acted in the Churches of God, before or ſince the Goſpel preached, Chriſt come in fleſh, as when the peace and proſperities of the world had procreated and matured pride. In the Church of the Jews it is evident, whileſt they were beſet with wars and troubles, though by ſome men and at ſome times
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40347:34"/> this ſin was acted, yet <hi>Solomons</hi> peace, plenty and glory, was attended with the eminencie of encreaſing various and glorious <hi>Altars, to Aſhteroth and Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com, and the gods of the Nations, to which his wives were related.</hi> And in the Chriſtian Church,<note place="margin">As <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Samo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatenus,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly gained riches, and puffed up with pride; uſurp'd ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeat and ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly throne, after the manner of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the world, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beiſance from the people by check and reviling termes: not much unlike <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden.</hi>
               </note> who knowes not that the ten preſſing perſecutions did generally by the humility of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, conſerve purity of Word and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, notwithſtanding the ſometime endeavours of particular hereticks, to ſubvert the ſame until the Churches peace and proſperity, conferred by <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the Chriſtian Emperour, gave occaſion for the proud man of ſin to appeare, and advance his abominations, increaſing his Altars, to the very caſting down of the Altar of God, in the greateſt part of the Chriſtian world, giving the Church, on ſad experience to complain the truth of that ſaying, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to be heard from heaven; <hi>Hodie venenum infunditur in Eccleſiam,</hi> Now is the poiſon of pride poured into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the Church: nay, my brethren,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40347:35"/> it is well, if we finde not on ſerious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, this ſin to be admitted and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced by ſuch, as preſent proſperity and external glory hath lifted up. And ſo I have done with the ſecond ground of Altar building, which muſt needs evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence it to be exceeding ſinful, whileſt acted from ſuch vile principles: I now paſſe to the third and laſt ground of this ſin: and that is</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Third ground of Altar-building.</note>
               <hi>Self-advancement and advantage:</hi> that curſed principle, which is inconſiſtent with ſincere affections to God and his worſhip: which hurrieth a man forward by right or wrong, to eſtabliſh his own glory, and poſſeſſe himſelf of creature tranſitory enjoyments: this is that which will make a man active for God, and his Altar, ſo long as ambitious ſelf can in that way obtain its object: but that once miſſed or obtained, affections abate, nay, are altogether alienated from the wayes of God: this uſeth Religion on a Machivilian account, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh their own throne, and keep up their own glory; ſo that whatſoever is but ſerviceable to this baſe end, though but for a ſeaſon, that ſhall be embraced and advanced. In a word,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40347:35"/> this is that curſed principle decried by Chriſt, in ſuch as take upon them the Profeſſion of his Name, as that which unſits them for adherencie to his Altar: yet this we ſhall finde clearly to be a ground of this grievous ſin of Altar-building, if we do but conſider, how <hi>the wages of unrighteouſneſſe engaged Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam,</hi> to go contrary to Gods Will, and by building many Altars in different places to attempt the curſing of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> contrary to Gods declared pleaſure, as in <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.23. <hi>chap.</hi> is to be ſeen; in which regard ſeducing Apoſtates, under the Goſpel Altar-builders, acted by this principle of ſelf-advantage and advancement, are ſaid <hi>to follow the way of Balaam, who loved the wages of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.15. and to be caſt away by the deceit of <hi>Balaams wages,</hi> Jude 11. ſo alſo we ſhall finde this principle provoking this ſin of Altar-building in <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> when he rebelled againſt the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin in the ſame way with himſelf: if we do but obſerve the Holy Ghoſt expreſſely noting his ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a uſurped Miniſtery, to this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry end, that he might ſtabliſh his u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40347:36"/> Magiſtracie, and his ſetting up his Altars at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> to be grounded on his deſire and deſign, to ſettle the Crown on his rebellious head; <hi>for,</hi> ſaith the text, <hi>Jeroboam thought in his heart, If this people go up and do ſacrifice at Jeruſalem, then ſhall the heart of this people turn again unto their Lord, even to Rehoboam King of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, ſo ſhall they kill me, and go again to Rehoboam: whereupon the King took coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Kings 12.26, 27, 28. <hi>et ad finem capitis:</hi> for uſurpers know, that the ſincere Worſhip of God teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth due ſubjection to their lawful So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignes: this ſelf-eſtabliſhment is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be the cauſe of <hi>Ahaz</hi> ſinful Altar-building: who (his faith not fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the living God of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) feared his approaching fall, and hoping to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh his throne, built Altars to the gods of <hi>Damaſcus;</hi> as we ſee, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.23, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. This curſed principle of ſelf-advancement was it, which did actuate the ſpirit of <hi>Jehu,</hi> with readineſſe and reſolution to do the work of the Lord, to the demoliſhing of the houſe, and deſtruction of the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> ſo as to call <hi>Jonadab to ſee his zeal for the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40347:36"/> Lord of Htſtes,</hi> ſo long as this work of the Lord was concurrent with, and conducing to his own eſtabliſhment; but when theſe two may be divided and diſtinct, his zeal abates, and himſelf can follow the way of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> to own the Altars at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> 2 Kings 10. As under the Law we finde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely the ſin of Altar-building, to be the ſad fruit of ſelf-advancement: ſo we ſhall ſee clearly, that from the ſame root doth it alſo ſpring, under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, all declinings of the Altar of Gods true worſhip, wayes and doctrine, and following after innovated principles and practices, thoſe falſe and oppoſite Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, ſpring and get ſtrength, if we do but ſeriouſly obſerve the Apoſtles cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racterizing deceivers, ſeducing Apoſtate Altar-builders, <hi>to be lovers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, proud, high-minded, lovers of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures more then lovers of God,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.2, 4. ſuch as count gaine godlineſſe<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quaeſtum eſse pieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> ſic re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem eſſe quaeſtum, vel artem quaeſtuoſam, quia ſcilicet totum Chriſtianiſmum lucro metiuntur. <hi>Calvin loc.</hi>
               </note>, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.5. ſuch as have hearts exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed (with might and ſtrength, as the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40347:37"/> Orig.)<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ideo ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolus uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur plura<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>li nume<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ro, ut o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendat, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductores illos non uno ava<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiae morbo laborare n c unam duntaxat artem cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere, divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rfas nefáſque congerou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, ac ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciores pecunia e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mungendi. <hi>Ger. in loc.</hi>
               </note> with covetouſneſſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. Such as followed the way of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam,</hi> and were caſt away with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of unrighteouſneſſe, (as I noted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) nay the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> affirmes, that through covetouſneſſe they <hi>make merchandiſe of ſoules,</hi> 2 Pet. 23. And St. <hi>John</hi> in his third Epiſtle, the ninth vetſe, notes <hi>Diotrephes</hi> corrupt practice to ſpring from this, that he loved to have the preheminence. Should we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe clear Scripture-inſtanced-evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, adde examples out of other hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories: who ſhall obſerve the devil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing his Turkiſh inſtruments, to crown apoſtacy from the Chriſtian Religion, with the honourable order of<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. hiſt. of Turks.</note> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melukes, and<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 107. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 91. the latter ſet up by <hi>Cara Rusthemes,</hi> a Doctor of the Mah<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>metane Law.</note> Janizaries, but muſt needs conclude advancement to be the proper way to ſeduce a ſelfiſh ſpirit from the Altar of God? This was the very ground which led<note n="(c)" place="margin">In <hi>p.</hi> 337.</note> 
               <hi>Mahomet</hi> the firſt Turkiſh Emperour, to faile the hopes of his mother, and the expectation of the Chriſtians, by embracing the Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40347:37"/> Altar, and abhorring the Chriſtian to which he was educated: ſelf-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment in his treacherouſly obtained Empire, was the principle that enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged<note n="(d)" place="margin">In <hi>p.</hi> 144.</note> 
               <hi>Michael Paleologus,</hi> to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Chriſtian liberty the Greek Churches did enjoy, unto the Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian yoke, and Papal tyrannie of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the tenth; nay, we might ſhew that the deſire of being reputed a Saint and ſhame of being ſhut out of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Church, was that which gave occaſion to<note n="(e)" place="margin">Euſeb. Eccl. hiſt. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Marcion,</hi> his here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Altar-building: and the proud af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectation of the dignity of a Biſhop, was the cauſe of<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 42.</note> 
               <hi>Novatus</hi> ſinful ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, and uncharitable opinions. What ſhall we ſay of <hi>Cerinthus, Samoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus, Manes, Arrianus, &amp;c.</hi> thoſe great Altar-builders againſt Gods Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, is it not eaſie to ſee ſelf-advancement to have been the bellowes which did blow their falſe fire: nay, will not our own experience, of the pride and ſelf-advancement of the Authors or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgers of innovated principles and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, clearly evidence this ſin of Altar-building to be the fruit of that bitter root, and ſo to be exceeding vile, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40347:38"/> to be ſeen unto by the ſincere worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers?</p>
            <p>And thus I have done with the firſt thing propounded, to ſet forth the vile and ſinful nature of Altar-building, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods Altar; which, unleſſe men may gather grapes of thiſtles, and figs of thornes, ſincere worſhippers of God cannot but conceive to be exceeding vile and ſinful, whileſt the odious and bitter fruit of ſhameful novelty, ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling pride, and ſelf-advantage and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement. I now come to ſhew the ſecond thing that ſets forth its vileneſſe, <hi>(viz) its ſinful actings:</hi> which if we finde but anſwerable to the grounds of it, muſt needs render it a ſin ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, that it is not only to be difreliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but with all power in their proper places to be reſiſted, by the ſincere wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of Gods Altar: and in this ſinful work, the Actors contract upon themſelves the guilt of a threefold ſinful acting: 1. <hi>A receding from God.</hi> 2. <hi>A rendering our wills the rule of divine Worſhip.</hi> And 3. <hi>A rebellion against the divine Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt ſinful act in building Altars, beſides the Altar of God, is <hi>the rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40347:38"/> from tht Lord,</hi> a forſaking of, and departing from God, not only when we directly and immediately change the object, and ſet up Altars unto ſtrange gods, ſtocks and ſtones, idols which are no gods, which muſt needs be granted to be the effect of <hi>a receding from the Lord:</hi> but when we withdraw from the matter or forme of Gods worſhip, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then we may be, and are juſtly ſaid to depart from the true God. To with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from God, and to embrace ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther object in his ſtead, are two diſtinct acts, and ever diſtinctly noted in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture with diſtinguiſhing termes; the one may be done, where the other doth not immediately, if ever, follow; for as a wicked wife may depart from her husband moſt treacherouſly, and yet marrieth not another: ſo may men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from God, and not ſo much as em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace any divine object in the room thereof, but with Atheiſts, <hi>ſay in their heart, There is no God:</hi> nay, uſually the departing from God in declining his Altar and Worſhip goes before, and is the way to embracing ſtrange gods, or entertaining meer Atheiſme; this the Church, wanting the Ordinances, Altar,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40347:39"/> and true Worſhip of the true God was afraid of,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> on the place.</note> (as ſome note in the dayes of <hi>Jeroboam</hi>) when ſhe prayes and cries earneſtly, to know <hi>where the flocks of God did reſt,</hi> urging the argument of her preſent danger; <hi>Why ſhould I turne aſide by the flocks of thy companions?</hi> (ſo calling themſelves,) <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.7. and the ten tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> were drawn from God before they worſhipped at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel;</hi> for the receding from the cauſe muſt needs be a refuſing of the effect; denial of Gods Altar is the declining of communion with God. As in the Ordinances and at the Altar of God, men are ſaid to <hi>draw nigh unto the Lord, to appear before him, or in his preſence,</hi> as, Levit. 10.2. Pſal. 42.4. ſo the turning from them may be juſtly termed <hi>a turning from the Lord,</hi> being a declining of that matter, and that forme God hath preſcribed himſelf to be enjoyed, and to enjoy his people by, ſo that if any do objective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depart from God, by changing their God, they will be juſtly charged, not only <hi>to depart from God,</hi> but alſo <hi>to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip idols, to change their god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the fountain of living waters, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40347:39"/> to dig ciſternes that hold no water,</hi> Jer. 2.11, 13. and therein they commit two evils; but if they refuſe to worſhip God at his Altar, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd according to his own declared Will, if they corrupt the matter of Gods Worſhip, or adulterate the forme of their adminiſtration, they are juſtly charged with a going from God: thus God by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> in <hi>chap.</hi> 65.11. chargeth the people with a forſaking him, in that they <hi>forget his holy mountaine:</hi> and by the Prophet <hi>Malachi, chap.</hi> 2.8. he upbraids the Prieſts with <hi>a departing out of his way,</hi> for corrupting of his Covenant and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: and the Authour to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes</hi> exhorts to a conſtant adherence to the adminiſtrations of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, according to the Goſpel-forme, denominating the declining of it, <hi>a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from the living God,</hi> Heb. 3 13. In Altar-building, as in other actions, there is conſiderable the terme from which before, the terme to which they move, and ſo the firſt act in this grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſin is in Scripture-phraſe in the Old and New Teſtament, denominated a forſaking of God in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he complaints of the ſincere, as, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.10. the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40347:40"/> chsrges of the ſinne by the Prophets, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.5, 24.20.24. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.4. and by the confeſſions of the penitent, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 10.10. <hi>Ezr</hi> 9 10. when <hi>Reheboam</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to joyn battel with <hi>Ieroboam</hi> declares the grounds of his confidence, amongſt others this is not the leaſt, that they by changing the matter of divine Worſhip,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 13.10, 11.</note> or the Prieſtly forme of adminiſtration, ordained of God, and ſo proceeding to the ſin of Altar-building, they had not forſaken their God, as had the ten tribes: and in the very ſtory to which our text refers, we finde the ſuſpected Altar-building branded with this epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thete, <hi>a turning aſide from following the Lord,</hi> Joſh. 22.16, 18, 23. And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel ſuch as turn from the truth to innovations, are ſaid <hi>to depart from the faith,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.1. <hi>to forſake the way of truth,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.15. <hi>and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the living God,</hi> Heb. 3.12. So that Gods charge upon the Altar-building Jewes may be charged on all Altar-builders, <hi>As a wife that treacherouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly departeth from her husband, ſo have ye dealt with me,</hi> Jer. 12.20. Is it not a vile thing, ſinful and ſadly provoking amongſt men, for ſouldiers to forſake
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40347:40"/> their colours, children their Parents, and wives their husbands? how much more vile muſt that ſin be, whereby creatures forſake their Creator, the redeemed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from their Redeemer? they that are naturally bent to purſue ſolid ſatisfying comforts, forſake the fountain of living waters: nay; and how fooliſh muſt it be to provoke, <hi>by turning from that preſence from which we cannot flee?</hi> moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and hills, hell and darkneſſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hide, and that power which we can neither reſiſt nor eſcape, but it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſinful Altar-builders that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him, to cover them with ſhame, and to write them in the duſt, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.13. Thus then by this firſt act, we canot but ſee this ſin to be ſo very ſinful, and to be ſpeedily ſeen to by ſincere Worſhippers of God.</p>
            <p>The ſecond act in Altar-build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, <hi>the rendring our own wills the rule of the Lords Worſhip,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the expreſſe prohibition a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which is right in our own eyes, and ſo ſinfully ſubjecting a divine ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the obedience of humane plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: and a ſoveraign God and Creator to ſuch matter and meaſure of ſervice, as ſuits to the fancie of a fraile, ignorant,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40347:41"/> ſinful creature to yield: which is in its nature ſo vile and ſhameful, that it may make every ſoul that ſeriouſly conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it, to bluſh and tremble to think that fraile man ſhould once preſume to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe obedience to be yielded to a great God: whilſt nature it ſelf teacheth, that all ſuperiour objects of ſervice and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience muſt dictate the Laws,<note place="margin">Deut. 12.8.</note> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the forme in which they will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce and receive content. Is it not below ſupream authority, to ſee the Lawes deſpiſed, and obedience yielded according to the ſubjects fancie? What father could brook his ſons obedience according to his own will? what Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral would reliſh his armies ſubjection after its own conceit? <hi>Obedience after the will of the ſubject is the ſubverſion of authority and ſupremacy, and exemption from the charge of rebellion in every acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though never ſo vile.</hi> How much leſſe ſhal the God of Heaven endure to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robed of his Soveraignty, in being denied the Prerogative of preſcribing his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſervice and obedience? This God would not admit in the evil Angels, but for their attempt thereof, caſt them into utter darkneſſe. And if God would not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:40347:41"/> leave man to the libertie of his will, in the obedience he ſhould yield his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour in the eſtate of his innocencie, when he was in a capacity of yielding perfect and pleaſing obedience, but would proclaim his Soveraignty by the preſcription of ſome ſpecial act of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, as the approvement of his due ſubjection, how much leſſe ſhall the ſons of men think to ſatisfie his Will, by following their own inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſince their fall, with the attempt of which, to everlaſting reproach humane nature ſtands ſtigmatized, as the thing which caſt the ſame out of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe? We ſhall finde God ſo exact in his ſervice, that he conſtituting <hi>Iſrael</hi> his choſen people to beare his Name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Nations,<note place="margin">Moſem in cultu Dei eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xit ad Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſte exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar, ut nihil formaret in terra, niſi quod congruum eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet archetypo ex coelis exhibito. Non habiturus id gratum aut ratum quicquid ex ſito cerebro praeter illud effinxiſſet. <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in loc.</hi> Nunc de forma agitur, etiam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum externarum ad cultum Dei pertinentium, quam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit Deus humano arbitrio relinquere, ſed eam ipſe praeſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re &amp; determinare. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vel. in Ex.</hi>
               </note> leaves them not to worſhip him according to their own will, but gives them lawes, and ſtatutes, and ordinances, and by his terrible ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance on Mount <hi>Sinai:</hi> his ſevere,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40347:42"/> judgements, and ſerious charge of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> engageth them to the obſervance thereof: nay, ſo exact is he in his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice, the very inſtruments and forme of the adminiſtration, that he gives <hi>Moſes</hi> a patterne of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, and all other things, requiring and ſtraitly charging every thing to be done according to the paterne ſhewed in the Mount, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.9, 40. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5. the due obſervance of which, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved <hi>Moſes</hi> faithful in Gods houſe. It is the obſervation of Dr. <hi>Willet,</hi> that <hi>the forme of the Tabernacle is not left to the will of man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Willet. Hexapla in Exod. p. <hi>595.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>no not to the judgement of Moſes; to teach us that God will not be worſhipped with will-morſhip, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the devices and inventions of men, but as himſelf hath appointed:</hi> the which we may alſo infer from <hi>Davids</hi> care, concerning the edification of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when he not only leaves his charge on <hi>Solomon</hi> his ſon to do this work, (intended by himſelf) but alſo to do it <hi>according to the patern he delivered him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">By ſome Prophet of God, who revealed all that ſhould be done to the Temple, as he had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently told <hi>Moſes</hi> the form of the Tabernacle. <hi>Diod. in loc.</hi>
               </note> enforcing his charge with this very reaſon, <hi>All this God made me to underſtand
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40347:42"/> in writing, by his hand upon me, even all the work of this patterne,</hi> 1 Chon. 28.11, 12, 19. therefore called <hi>the paterne of all that was with him by the Spirit;</hi> by all which we may ſee the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign God challenging, (which is his due) the prerogative of preſcribing his own worſhip, and the very inſtruments and forme thereof, yet ſuch is the vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of corrupt nature, that though God complain of the ſin in the Jewes, that <hi>their feare of him was taught by the precepts of men,</hi> Iſ. 29.13. and Chriſt char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth and aggravateth their ſin by the ſame, aſſerting, <hi>that in vain men worſhip him, teaching for doctrines the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men,</hi> Mat. 15.9. that the ſons of men are apt to meaſure the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip they will yield to God by the rule of their own will: in which regard ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Altar-builders are (in Scripture-phraſe) commonly ſaid to forſake <hi>the Covenant,</hi> Deut. 29.25. 1 Kings 19.10. and <hi>Commandments of God,</hi> Ezra 9.10. and <hi>Law of the Lord,</hi> Jer. 9.13. <hi>the right way,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.15. and to follow <hi>their own inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> after which, to the provocation of divine juſtice, they <hi>go a whoring,</hi> as,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40347:43"/> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.29, 39. of which God will take vengeance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.8. in which regard the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> calls ſeduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the truth of the doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt, though upon never ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent pretences of Piety, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or will-worſhip,<note place="margin">Opera hominum nominat omnes cultus quos ſinc mandato Dei inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuunt, &amp; in quibus cultum aliquem religionis collocant, bonâ ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quâ (ut lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui ſolent) intentione. <hi>Mal. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23. the which he condemns, and cautions Chriſtians to take heed of, as having only a ſhew of wiſdom, but being indeed ſinful foole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; ſo that thus we ſee men, whoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are ſubjects to motion <hi>à quo ad quem,</hi> being in the firſt act looſed from the Altar and Worſhip of God in the ſin of Altar-building, not capable of living without ſome religion or other; In the ſecond act, conſult their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, and erect an Altar and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip unto God, according to their own will; although to the ſhame of men it be regiſtred in ſacred record, <hi>that God made man upright, and he ſought out ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inventions,</hi> Eccl. 7.29, Thus then I have done with the ſecond act of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar-builders,<note place="margin">Erat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ab ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, ſed curioſitate ſua, Dei verbo non contentus, ſibi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum aſcivit &amp; toti poſteritati. <hi>Mer. in loc.</hi>
               </note> the rendering their own
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40347:43"/> wills the rule of their obedience, and now paſſe to the third act.</p>
            <p>The third act is, <hi>rebellion againſt God, and againſt the authority to which God hath committed the charge of his Altar;</hi> and to ſtand on the proving this at large, were but time and paines ſpent in vain, whileſt I ſhould but do what is done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: for having cleared the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer acts of this ſin, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that it is a receſſion from God, and rendering our own wills the rule of divine worſhip; I have cleared the premiſes, which muſt needs enforce this Concluſion, for theſe two are the integral and eſſential parts of rebellion, according to which it is denominated: for when men go from the Covenant and Commandments of God, what do they otherwiſe then ſtand oppoſite to him, with a ſtubborne will, uttering the rebellious language of the rebellious Gentiles, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Let us break his bands in ſunder, and caſt his cords from off us?</hi> and thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Citizens ſpoken of in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, in <hi>Luke</hi> 19.14. whoſe meſſage was, <hi>We will not have this man to reign o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us:</hi> and hence the words, which in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40347:44"/> the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>As <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Vid. <hi>Leigh</hi> Crit. ſacr. <hi>Bux.</hi> Lex. Scapulae. The Septuagint do ſo uſe it. See alſo Mr. <hi>Medes</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtaſie of latter times. <hi>p.</hi> 5. where he interprets Apoſtaſie to be a rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </note> Greek and Hebrew are commonly uſed to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie rebellion, are alſo u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſignifie <hi>defection, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquencie,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtaſy</hi> or <hi>turning aſide</hi> from God; ſo that theſe ſeveral words in our language are and may be ſynonom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or of the ſame ſignification, to expreſſe the ſame ſin: and hence alſo all rebellion is ſaid to be a defection from the ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours to whom they owe ſubjection: yet might I give inſtances in Scripture, where this ſin is called a rebellion, and ſtubborne oppoſition of God, as <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> and his company, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16, 17. <hi>ch.</hi> and <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> nay all the Altar-build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Princes of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> are ſaid <hi>to rebel againſt the Lord,</hi> when they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after idols in the acting of this ſin; but why go I to look inſtances, at this diſtance, when the very text deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates it thus: ſaying, <hi>Rebel not againſt the Lord, and rebel not againſt us?</hi> only this you may take notice of in the text, that the terme Rebel not againſt the Lord, comes from the ſame root in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:40347:44"/> the Hchrew, from which is derived <hi>Nimrod,</hi> the name of that great Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er before (or as <hi>Auguſtine, Hierom,</hi> and others of the Ancients againſt) the Lord, if he were ſo called from his <hi>Apoſtaſie, defection and rebellion:</hi> his rebellion was ſo great, as that his name is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbially given to every rebellious ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, by way of alluſion to him: he is noted to be the head of that rebellious work againſt God, which we read of in <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. and that from a very probable conjecture, ſeeing in Scripture that place of <hi>Babel</hi> is called his Kingdome, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.10. his rebellious act was this very ſin of Altar-building, if (as <hi>Hugo</hi> notes) he was the firſt bringer in of idolatry,<note place="margin">Hugo in Annot. in Gen. Joſeph. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq. c. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> teaching men to worſhip the fire, or as <hi>Joſephus,</hi> that he excited men to contemn God and follow for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in their own united power, and ſo was the firſt founder of idolatry, of whoſe minde is Dr. <hi>Willet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Willets Hexa. in Gen. <hi>10.9.</hi>
               </note> conceiving him to be the ſame whom forreigne ſtory calls <hi>Belus,</hi> and makes the firſt founder of their Babylonian Monarchy, of whom the Gentiles in the Eaſterne parts of the world, called their idols, <hi>Belial, Beelzebub, Belphegor.</hi> You ſee
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40347:45"/> then clearly that Altar-builders, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from God, and following their own ways, do rebel againſt the Lord: which muſt needs render the ſin exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vile in the eyes of ſuch as are the Lords ſubjects; for what ſpot of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie and reproach can be caſt on the ſons of men more odious and hateful then <hi>rebellion?</hi> what is ſo immediately and highly provoking unto Soveraignty as <hi>rebellion?</hi> for moſt clement Princes muſt needs with a ſevere hand chaſtiſe rebellion: ſuch is the vile nature of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, that found in children againſt the Parents, by Gods Ordinance among the Jewes, the ſubject of it muſt be ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſtones, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.18, 19, 20. And when <hi>Moſes</hi> would exalt Gods mercies to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he aggravates their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe by charging them to have been <hi>a ſtiffe-necked and rebellious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Deut,</hi> 9.6, 23, 24. And <hi>Samuel</hi> charging <hi>Saul</hi> with this guilt, aſſerts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion to be as the ſin of witchcraft for its vile nature. And when <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies would make her vile, they wil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominate her <hi>a rebellious City,</hi> Ezra 4.12, 15. And did ever any yet <hi>rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord and proſper?</hi> let the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40347:45"/> judgements of God upon <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> for their rebellions witneſſe. Whil'ſt then this ſin of Altar-building ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears ſo vile, not only in the ground, but alſo the acts thereof, let all ſincere wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers at Gods Altar conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their loyalty to their great Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and gracious Redeemer do not engage them in their places, to ſee to ſo great and crying a ſin.</p>
            <p>The third thing that may evidence building Altars, beſide the Altar of God, to be a ſin exceeding ſinful, is <hi>the ſad effects thereof,</hi> which we cannot but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be exceeding ſad and bitter, whileſt the root and branches thereof are ſo exceeding vile; for the fruit muſt needs be ſuitable to the tree that beares it: and thoſe are theſe foure.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A rending from the body of the Church,</hi> a withdrawing from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion God himſelf hath ſet us in; a making a ſchiſme and rent in the Church of God: as <hi>Diodate</hi> notes, a ſevering our ſelves from the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church: in which alone is the true ſervice of God, and the participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his grace and Covenant, that ſad effect of ſins Soveraignty among the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:40347:46"/> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.4. which is ſo evil, that the Propagators thereof are to be declined, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. which violates unity, and deprives the Church of that bleſſed fruit of the Spirit: this is that which as nature condemnes in the body, ſo the Goſpel in the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.25. which when making factions and parties in the Church, as ſedition in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, is dangerous, and many times de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive, being attended and ſeconded with envies, ſtrifes, hatred and the like; yet this evil fruit ſprings from Altar-building as its ſad effect, as is evident in the ſtory under conſideration, wherein it is clear, that the two Tribes ſuſpected the act in hand to be to this end, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from any longer communion with their brethten, and to worſhip God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and by themſelves: which they deſire to prevent by rather giving them inheritances on the ſame ſide of the river with them,<note place="margin">See more of this ſchiſme, Mr. <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linſworths</hi> Rejoynder to Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> and Mr <hi>Tailors</hi> Reply.</note> then the diviſion of portions ſhould divide their piety and joynt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance on Gods Altar: So <hi>Corah</hi> and his company did rend themſelves from the body of the Church, and make a fearful diviſion in refuſing to keep com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the people of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40347:46"/> to his appointed adminiſtration, in <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. when they were about to erect their Altar againſt Gods: what a ſad rent from the Church did <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboams</hi> Altar-building make? not to this day ſemented, though ſought after by ſuch as earneſtly ſupplicate the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of the gracious Promiſe of God, <hi>that the ſtick of Ephraim, and the ſtick of Judah ſhall become one in his hand,</hi> in <hi>Ezek</hi> 37. from 16, to 21. In which is to be noted that the accompliſhment thereof, is promiſed to be accompanied with the aboliſhment of their Altar-building ſin, and unity in Gods wayes and worſhip, <hi>v.</hi> 22, unto the end of the chapter: which grievous rent from the communion of the Church, a burden not to be borne by the ſincere worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers at Gods Altar, provokes (as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noted out of Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">His Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition on <hi>Canticles.</hi>
               </note>) that pathetical prayer to be directed to the true Church and Altar of Chriſt, in <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.7. that they might be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the danger thereof: nay, it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded not only the Prieſts and Levites to prefer the Altar and Church of God above their ſuburbs and poſſeſſions, but alſo <hi>all ſuch as ſet their heart to ſeek the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40347:47"/> Lord,</hi> to run the hazard of going to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to ſacrifice unto the Lord with their brethren, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.13, 14, 16. This ſad effect doth the Spirit witneſſe to follow this ſin, nay, flow from it under the Goſpel; The Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 20.30. foreſeeing the appearance of ſeducers, Apoſtate-Altar-builders, that would innovate doctrines and formes of worſhip, contrary to Chriſts inſtitution, chargeth the Elders of the Epheſian Church to ſee to this ſin, at leaſt that their members be not ſeduced; urging this ſad effect as a ſwaying reaſon, <hi>They ſhall draw aſide many diſciples after them: from the communion of the Church,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>[Ut ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducant] ab Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate: [poſt ſe] ad inhaeren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus. <hi>Dyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſ. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſ. in loc.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here autem ſignificat inani gloria tumidos compellere ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatores in ſua nomina jurare. <hi>Aret. in loc.</hi> as did <hi>Novatus vid. Euſeb. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>Religionum Confuſio diſſipat Eccleſiae conſenſionem. <hi>Maſ. in Text.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> ſaith one, or make ſects, ſaith another; and the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> in the ſecond Epiſtle, the ſecond chapter, the third verſe propheſies, falſe teachers ſhould be in the Chriſtian Churches, which building their owne Altars of damnable doctrines, many ſhould follow their pernicious wayes, ſpeaking evil of the way of truth: for the confuſion of Religion muſt needs be
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40347:47"/> deſtructive to the concord of the Churches, which God witneſſed by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting one only Altar for all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples attendance, with one only forme of adminiſtration, and this cannot but be ſeen in the Apoſtles dayes, by ſuch as ſhall ſeriouſly obſerve the Apoſtolical redargution of ſchiſmes and ſeducers, characterizing falſe apoſtles, charging the Churches to obſerve and decline them, as thoſe that make diviſions and trouble them: frequent commendations of the union and communion of the Church and diſciples, and fervent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion to, and prayers for the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace: which all ſuggeſt to us, and clearly imply, that this ſin of Altar-building by will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, was in act to the dividing of the members from the body in their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dayes, and who is there, that look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into Eccleſiaſtical ſtory,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dyonyſ.</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaxndri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> his Epiſtle to <hi>Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> recited by <hi>Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phil. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 45. <hi>or tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlat.</hi> 44.</note> ſees not the ſad rentings from, and confuſions in the Church, effected by the Altar-building (of doctrines) diſſonant to truth, and the Altar of Chriſt, propagated by the many hereticks of the primitive times, as <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatus,</hi> whom <hi>Dionyſius</hi> in his Epiſtle to him chargeth with a renting and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40347:48"/> from the Church, as a ſin moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, counting <hi>the ſuffering for the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Church a more glorious mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome, then the ſufferings for not ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing to devils?</hi> for this is ſuffered for one ſoul, that for the univerſal Church. So alſo the Donatiſts, Manichees, <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Samoſatenus,</hi> of whom the Synod of <hi>Antioch</hi> ſadly complaine, <hi>that the Church was ſo rent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See their Epiſtle in <hi>Euſeb. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 30.</note> 
               <hi>that faith and religion was run, into great ſpite, hatred, and ſlander, by reaſon of his ſwelling pride,</hi> as alſo by the Arrians, which filled the whole Chriſtian world with confuſion and diviſion; ſome taking this ſide, and ſome that; ſome communicating here, and ſome there, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to moſt bloody perſecution of the true ſincere Miniſters and people of God, the which ſchiſme, how ſadly complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of by <hi>Athanaſius</hi> the good Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> how earneſtly endeavoured to be cemented by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the good Emperour, and how ſtrongly it reigned to the checking of the Churches com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and clouding of the glory of the the Goſpel: <hi>Euſebius</hi> at large de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, in his firſt and ſecond books of Eceleſiaſtical hiſtory; but may not the ſeparations from the communion of the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40347:48"/> Church, and ſad ſchiſmes amongſt our ſelves, produced by ſuch as are of late ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen up to build Altars of innovated do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, contrary to the doctrine of Chriſt, call us back from wandring ſo far to ſeek confirmation of this ſad effect of ſo grievous a ſinne, and provoke us with ſhame and ſorrow, to own the evident effect upon our own ſad experience, and ſet to our ſeales, that of a truth Altar-building againſt Gods Altar is an odious, becauſe a Church-renting ſin?<note place="margin">Socrates Scholacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, Eccl. hiſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>10</hi>
               </note> for to how many may we ſay, as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour to <hi>Aretius</hi> the Novatian Biſhop, <hi>Why ſever ye your ſelves from the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the faithful?</hi> whoſe anſwer may occaſion our reply as his: <hi>Provide you a ladder to climbe into Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond effect which muſt needs alſo ſhew the building Altars, beſide the Altar of God, to be exceeding ſinful, is (to ſpeak with due reverence) <hi>a run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God upon ſtraits, concerning the diſpenſations of his Providences, and the adminiſtration of his judgements or mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies;</hi> not that God is in his nature capable of ſuch want of wiſdome, who is the moſt wiſe, and readily diſpoſeth all
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40347:49"/> things according to the counſel of his own will: or weakneſſe of power to effect and bring about his purpoſe, whoſe power is like himſelf, and not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted as that is, ſhould make him to doubt or diſpute what to do,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Luctatur in Deo hinc juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia &amp; ira adverſus peccata, quae atro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cantes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trociter puniri &amp; perdi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulat: il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linc im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſa mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordia &amp; bonitas, quae non vult mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris, ſed ut conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur &amp; vivat. <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. in Hoſ.</hi> 11.8</p>
                  <p>Hac particula oſtendit Deus quid meriti ſunt Iſraeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, &amp; jam ſe propenſum eſſe ad ſumendam poenam quâ digni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſunt: non tamen id ſine poenitentia vel ſaltem dubitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. <hi>Calv. in l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> whether to ſtrike or ſpare the ſinner. But to ſpeak to our capacity, ſuch may be ſometimes the effects of divine Providence, that to us God may ſeem to be in a ſtrait, and, as it were, in doubt with himſelf; his juſtice provoked by the ſin, putting for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to puniſh the ſinner; and his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies deſiring repentance and deliverance, pleading for ſuſpence or abatements of the afflictions ſtriving together, make God (as it were) cry out, <hi>What ſhall I do unto thee? how ſhall I give thee, up E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim? how ſhall I deliver thee, Iſrael? how ſhall I make thee as Admah? how ſhall I ſet thee as Zeboim?</hi> Wherein though this Altar-building <hi>Iſrael</hi> had deſerved to be made as <hi>Admah</hi> and <hi>Zeboim</hi> for their ſinne, yet God doth ſeemingly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40347:49"/> with himſelf, how ſhould he do it to them: in <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.8. ſuch another ſtrait God ſeems to be in, when he ſtands over <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with his <hi>how long?</hi> and <hi>when ſhall it once be?</hi> as in <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.27. where he cri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s out of this ſin of Altar-building, <hi>I have ſeen thine adulteries and neighings, the lewdneſſe of thy whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and thy abominations on the hills in the field<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; Wo unto thee, O Ieruſalem!</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, I have ſeen all Altars, and am ready to ſtrike and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thee ſeverely for them: but yet he checks himſelf, and bids a ſtay to his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, with a wilt thou not be made clean? when ſhall it once be? I would faine have my hand ſtayed, at laſt, even at laſt before the ſtroak that is up, fall: and as mercie and juſtice, thoſe different properties in God, are (to ſpeak with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of a God not in the leaſt ſubject to paſſions) ſet, as it were, oppoſite by this ſin; ſo alſo we ſhall ſee a ſeeming ſtrife betweene Gods purity, that cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure iniquity, and divine glory which he will not in the leaſt give to another, and promiſe performance, faithfulneſſe: for the ſin being acted, God forſaken, his Law declined, and mans will and inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40347:50"/> advanced, then Gods purity pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes divine juſtice to ſtrike with ſuch language as this; <q>I am holy, I cannot endure ſin, yet it is acted againſt me; If ſentence be not ſpeedily executed, the heart of men will be fully ſet in them to do wickedly; patience will but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke their prophaneneſſe, they being ſo corrupt as to abuſe it, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.11. will be as it were driven to ſin by it, nay, they will make divine ſilence an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſins allowance; and when they ſleight my ſervice, and ſet up their owne inventions, and yet go on and proſper, and I hold my tongue, they will ſay, I am altogether ſuch an one as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; ariſe, juſtice, let me not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted the Author or indulger of ſuch diſobedience, ſet their ſins in order be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21. Nay, though they being deareſt <hi>Davids,</hi> doth not their ſin give occaſion to mine enemies to blaſpheme? ſhould I ſuffer <hi>Jedidiah,</hi> my beloved one, to increaſe his worſhip at Idol-Altars, and corrupt, nay, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline mine and his poſterity to poſſeſſe his Kingdome? will not the Heathen ſay, I am not pure and holy, for I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge their ſin? Do not the lewd lives
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:40347:50"/> of Chriſtians cauſe the Heathen to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the Goſpel of my Sonne, and to ſay my doctrine dictates ſuch things as nature will bluſh to ſee? as if nature (which I made) were more pure then my ſelfe; ſhall I be ſilent and not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the impieties of my people, which make Heathen <hi>Romes</hi> Senators when they ſee my holy Word, to queſtion whether it be my Law: Shall my divine nature be blaſphemouſly denied by an Apoſtate <hi>Julian,</hi> or <hi>Arius,</hi> and I not be avenged? Shall the perfidious and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious deeds of my Chriſtian people deny me to be a God, and provoke this Turkiſh appeale to my purity, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing the league ſworne in my name, and broken by them?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold, thou crucified Chriſt, this is the league thy Christians in thy Name made with me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">As did <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murath</hi> ſixth King of the Turks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſlaus</hi> king of <hi>Hungary</hi> &amp; <hi>Folonia,</hi> when he took abſolution from his oath from Cardinal <hi>Julian,</hi> and fought againſt the Turks, contrary to the league ſworne. See <hi>Turk. Hiſt.</hi> p. 297.</note> 
               <hi>which they have without cauſe violated; now if thou be a God, as they ſay thou art, and as we dreame, revenge the wrong now done unto thy Name, and me; and ſhew thy power on thy perjurious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who in their deeds deny thee their God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:40347:51"/>
            <p>And ſhall I not ariſe to chaſtiſe them? will not the honour of my holy Name and nature by ſevere judgements for their unholineſſe on thoſe my people, who will not ſhew it by their conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, obeying my Lawes, and fearing to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend my pleaſure: be vindicated from the blaſphemous thoughts of mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies?</p>
            <p>Unto which Gods power, glory, and faithfulneſſe ſtanding up, do (as it were) anſwer and plead, True O Lord, moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thy pure nature ſtands juſtly offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thy people are by their Altar-build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made naked in thy ſight; they have moved thee to jealouſie with that which is not God,<note place="margin">Deu. 32.21 22.</note> or of God: it may be juſt that the fire kindled againſt them in thy wrath, ſhould burne unto Hell, and that therein for their ſin, thou mayeſt ſcatter them into corners, and make their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memberance for to ceaſe, and thereby vindicate the glory of thy purity, and ſhew thy ſelfe a ſin-hating,<note place="margin">Exod. 32.22, 23.</note> by being a ſin-revenging God; but what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thy faithfulneſſe? the glory there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will be loſt in the midſt of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. O remember thy promiſe, Lord, thy promiſe made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> to <hi>Iſaac,</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:40347:51"/> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> and let not the Heathen ſay thou haſt ſpoken what thou wilt not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, thou art not as man that thou ſhouldſt lie, nor the ſonne of man that thou ſhouldeſt repent: O let the mouth of <hi>Balaam</hi> witneſſe to a curſing <hi>Balak,</hi> that thou haſt ſaid it, and thou wilt do it; thou haſt ſpoken it, and thou wilt make it good, <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.19. <q>How ſhall the Heathen alſo blaſpheme thy power, and ſay, becauſe thou waſt not able to bring to paſſe thy begun mercy, and give them the promiſed land: thou haſt ſlaine them in the wilderneſſe? <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.16. For, Lord, the Nations conſider not the cauſe, nor accknowledge thy juſtice, but reproach thy power, and promiſe, and ſay, For miſchief thou haſt begun to ſhew them mercy: Nay, they will not only reproach thy power and promiſe, but rob thee of thine honour, and the glory of thy juſtly inflicted fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; the rod will rebel againſt the hand that uſeth it; if now, and ſo ſeverely thou ſtrike with it: conſider, Lord, make not a full end of this rebellious Altar-building generation; for the enemies will behave himſelfe proudly, and ſay, My hand, and not the Lord,<note place="margin">Deu. 32.27</note> hath done
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:40347:52"/> all this:</q> ſo that ſinne doth not onely make Gods Word to fight againſt it ſelf in promiſes and threats, but alſo the very properties of the Lord: how ſad muſt it be unto an ingenuous child to ſee fury and mercy, power and pitie, juſtice and compaſſion at the ſame time to ſhine in the boſome of a tender father? how vile then muſt this ſinne be which runs God on ſuch ſtraits, when as much as in us lies, we labour to confound the very God of Wiſdome, and ſet unity at enmity, making the Divine nature, as it were, to warre againſt it ſelf? And hence it is that the properties of God are many times pleading expoſtulations with God, <hi>modo admonentis de benignitate,</hi> by way of hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble minding God of his owne nature in the prayers of his owne people, fearing or feeling the fierceneſſe of his fury.</p>
            <p>The third effect is, <hi>a rendering the worſhip of God vile in the eyes of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then which know him not:</hi> by this ſinne the enemies of the Lord have occaſion to blaſpheme the Name and ways of God, to reproach the Goſpel and Doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt: for in Altar-building men run from God, and actually ſpeak the language of the Apoſtate covenant-corrupting
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40347:52"/> Jewes, It is in vaine to ſerve God, and what profit have we that we have kept all his Ordinances? <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.14. and attribute the peace and plenty Gods patience indulgeth, unto the Queene of Heaven, and their ſhameful impieties, <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.17, 18. and therefore God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, that when his people built Altars unto <hi>Baal,</hi> they did not know that God gave her corne, and wine, and oyle, and multiplied their ſilver and gold, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.8. And God aggravates this ſinne ever with the mention of his mercies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he declares how little cauſe they had ſo really to vilifie his wayes and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, by departing from them: their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt his will and words, muſt needs beſpeak his yoake to be heavie and ſervile bondage, which is indeed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect freedome, and his tender reigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his people, to be fierce and cruel. The Schiſmes and ſad Diviſions produced by this ſinne, give occaſion to ſuch as know not the doctrine of unity, to charge the wayes and worſhip of God with the natural production thereof, never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how they are the fruits of ſinne, not of Gods ſacred Altar. How hath Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan and his wicked inſtruments taken oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40347:53"/> to reproach vilifie, and blaſpheme the wayes and worſhip of God from the lewdneſſe of ſome that profeſſe it in all ages; do not the Papiſts generally calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate the Reformation of the Church with the charge of <hi>diviſion and novelty,</hi> and the like? becauſe ſome profeſſing to it have divided from the Church, and propagated their Altar-building-princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: ſo that every obſervant eye cannot but ſee that Altar-building, beſides the Altar of God, makes Gods Altar, Word, and Worſhip, as <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> their curſed act on the circumciſed Scheche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, made good <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſavour to ſtink among the Canaanites and Perizzites: in which regard it lies on the ſincere wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of God with conſtancie to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to Gods Altar, and with courage to ſuppreſſe others in their places, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt effect of this ſinne of Altar-building, which may render it exceeding vile, is, <hi>a reviving of the Lords fury:</hi> for theſe are <hi>the Altars of Bethel which God will viſit,</hi> Amos 3.14. This is the ſinne that is <hi>written before the Lord as with a pen of iron, and point of a dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> Jer. 17.1, 2. This is the ſetting of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:40347:53"/> 
               <hi>poſt by his poſt, and threſhold by the Lords threſhold, to the defiling of Gods holy Name till the ſubjects be conſumed in his anger,</hi> Ezek. 43.8. This is the ſetting up <hi>the Altar of jealouſie</hi> to the provoking of God <hi>to depart from his Sanctuarie,</hi> Ezek. 8.6 This is the following new gods to the kindling of <hi>a fire in his wrath, which ſhall burne to hell,</hi> Deut. 32.21, 22. In a word, this is the golden Calfe, which turnes patience (to ſpeak with reverence) into ſuch rage, that a <hi>Moſes</hi> prayer can hardly binde from deſtroying, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.8, 9, 10. and the rebellion ſo highly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking that a God moſt gracious, in all affliction afflicted, in pitie and love ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and redeeming, being by it vexed in ſpirit, becomes an enemie, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9. How did <hi>Corah</hi> and his company by their but formal Altar-building, ſchiſmatical with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing from the adminiſtrations of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip, provoke the Lords wrath to the cauſing of the earth to open her mouth and ſwallow them up alive? How did <hi>Solomons</hi> Altars ſtir up divine diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to the rending away ten Trib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from his Kingdome, not to this day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored? What ſad monuments of divine juſtice and fury hath it made <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:40347:54"/> and <hi>Samaria:</hi> it were eaſie to evidence the increaſing property of this ſin; but this may ſuffice to ſuch as do but conſider the fierceneſſe of the Lords fury, which will make <hi>the mountaines to melt, and hills to ſhake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mic. i. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and Kings of the earth to tremble;</hi> for who can ſtand before his frown, much more fatal then the frowne of the moſt cruel Turkiſh tyrant threatening preſent death? Can this Lion roare, and the beaſts of the earth not tremble?<note place="margin">Amos 1.2.</note> If while his wrath is kindled but a little, they be happy that truſt in Chriſt; what terrour muſt poſſeſſe them that by their Altars-building are naked before it;<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.12. Exo. 32.25</note> ſo that the ſinne muſt needs be vile, to be avoided, and ſeaſonably ſeene to, that is ſo highly diſpleaſing unto God.</p>
            <p>I have now done with the third thing in the diſcovery of the ſinfulneſſe of building Altars beſide the Altar of God, <hi>(viz.) the vile effects</hi> which ſpring from it: which taſted by ſerious contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cannot but render it bitter in the mouth, and excite ſincere worſhippers of God againſt it; I ſhall only adde one thing more to the aggravation of its vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and that very briefly, and ſo paſſe to the Application of the Point, <hi>viz.</hi> the aggravating properties.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:40347:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The firſt aggravating property that may render Altar-building to be exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vile, is, <hi>the ſingularity of the ſubjects.</hi> Singularity is not ſavoury in any; it many times ſprings from pride, and beſpeaks an evil diſpoſition: this ſinne is many times acted by Gods people only, who know the true God, and have worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped at the true Altar: this ſin God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf aggravates with this very property, in <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.11. expoſtulating with them, <hi>Hath any Nation changed their gods, though they be no gods? and yet my people have changed their glory for that which will not profit:</hi> and, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. <hi>v.</hi> 5. the rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people which follow their owne thoughts, and burne incenſe upon Altars of Brick, have their ſin aggravated by their ſingularity; they ſay, <hi>Stand by thy ſelfe, come not neare me, I am holier then thou:</hi> as that which makes a ſmoak in Gods noſtrils, and a fire to burne all the day: ſo that this addes much to this vile ſinne: The iſſes of <hi>Chittim,</hi> and coaſt of <hi>Kedar</hi> will not afford a parallel, or ſhew ſuch a thing: for whilſt the Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſuſpecting any innovation againſt their <hi>Diana,</hi> run together with great zeal crying, <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians,</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:40347:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> and readily contend for their Idol-god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe and ſuperſtitious worſhip, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved not to change, though for a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and the Athenians, though given to novelty, think <hi>Paul</hi> odious in ſeeming to ſet forth new gods: the people of the true God are only ſeene to change ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the object, but many times the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar the true God hath preſcribed to be worſhipped at.</p>
            <p>The ſecond aggravating propertie of Altar-building is, that it is <hi>committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst ſtanding directions, dictated Lawes and Ordinances,</hi> Gods revealed will and pleaſure concerning his Altar and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: as it is <hi>Iſraels</hi> glory, that no Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſo great a Nation that hath ſuch Statutes and Judgements,<note place="margin">Deut. 7.</note> as all the Law of the Lord their God; ſo it is laid on them as the greater duty to take heed to themſelves, and to keep their ſoul dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, that they forget them not, but teach them to their ſons, &amp; ſons ſons, and obſerve to do them; it is alſo their great aggravation,<note place="margin">Acts 17, 13</note> that they forſake the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of their God, go away from his Statutes, forget his Lawes, caſt off his Commandments, to create to themſelves an Altar and Worſhip according to their
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40347:55"/> owne inventions: and though the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian ignorance may extenuate their ſuperſtitious worſhip at the Altar to the unknown God: yet now light is come abroad, and God calls to repentance, they muſt walk as children of the light; for ignorance can now be no plea, where preſcript rule is propoſed: now as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt a Kings Proclamation, and diſobedience againſt a fathers declared will, ſo is this Altar-building hainous and abominable, becauſe againſt directions ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited.</p>
            <p>The third aggravating property of this ſinne of Altar-building, is, that <hi>it ſhuts Gods eares againſt prayer.</hi> What is ſpoken of ſinnes in general, in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.2. <hi>Your ſins have hid his face from you, that he will not heare:</hi> is applicable, nay, applied to this ſinne in ſpecial, where God not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares that when <hi>Iſrael,</hi> his Altar-building people, did cry to him in their trouble, he would not hear them, <hi>Ier.</hi> 11.11. but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo prohibits the Prophets praying; <hi>Thou ſhalt not pray for this people, neither lift up a cry or prayer for them:</hi> and that is urged with a therefore, <hi>(viz.)</hi> becauſe, <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the numbers of the ſtreets of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, they have ſet up Altars,</hi> ver. 12, 13.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40347:56"/> Let me alone, <hi>Moſes,</hi> was the angry voice of God, produced by the Calf, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar at <hi>Horeb,</hi> Exod. 32.10. How juſt is it with God to deny the Petitions of them, that deny preſcriptions from him in the way of his owne worſhip? <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.25, to 33. For as children when ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly following their own<note n="*" place="margin">Si curſum vitae noſtrae propriis conſiliis regere vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumus, &amp; religionis fideique neg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tium ſecundum ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem noſtram inſtituere, idem nobis accidit quod pueris quos parentes primum docent incedere, &amp;c. <hi>Lav.</hi> in <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.31.</note> wills fall into harme, their cries are not compaſſionated by the tender parent: ſo deales God with his ſtubborne people that make their wills the way or rule of his divine worſhip.</p>
            <p>I have now done with the Doctrinal conſideration of the Point, and ſhall leave it to the judgements of the ſincere worſhippers at God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Altar, to conſider whether a ſinne ſpringing from ſuch cauſes, exerciſed in ſuch acts, producing ſuch effects, ſubject to ſuch aggravations, be not exceeding ſinful; and if but ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to be undertaken, ſufficient to ſtir the zeale of the ten tribes, to the reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance thereof, much to be ſeene to, ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, and ſoone ſuppreſſed, where it is,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:40347:56"/> really, and indeed acted: I ſhall now briefly apply to our more particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>The firſt Uſe of the point may be of enquiry and humiliation, to put us apon the ſearch whether in the midſt of us we may not ſee ſome of our brethren, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the ſame, and who have worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the ſame Goſpel-worſhip with our ſelves, to withdraw from the Altar of God, and erect Altars after their owne inventions; which if we finde, our hearts ſhould be heavie in us, and our eyes filled with tears: as humbling our ſelves for ſo grievous a guilt: and upon enquiry, he that is not wilfully blinde, cannot but ſee beyond the river in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> material, beſides formal Altars built beſides the Altar of God: five Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments innovated which God never inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted: objects of divine adoration ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, never by the Lord, or themſelves allowed: Sacrifices preſented for ſinne, which God never preſcribed: offices and orders of holy men and women main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, which in the Canon of Scripture are never mentioned, nor by the ſame warranted: principles preſſed as matters
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:40347:57"/> of faith neceſſary to ſalvation, and that on the paine of being branded with He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, ſuch as were never found in the Apoſtles Creed; but repugnant to it, prayers, penance, and many the like practices performed with much devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which are not only not warranted, but condemned in Scripture as ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and will-worſhip, and diſſonant to reaſon in the very light of nature; all which may be matter of mourning to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very gracious heart to ſee, although in a ſubject ſomewhat remote: but more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if when in mercie God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us from ſerving at, or ſuffering for not ſerving at ſuch Altars as did our progenitors; and whileſt we our ſelves profeſſe a reformation of the Altar of God, Goſpel-worſhip and Ordinances, we ſhall even at home finde Altars of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other kinde erected, and erecting: it may be ſome caſting off Gods Altars of Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Ordinances, not worſhipping in any external and formal adminiſtration, but by their owne pretended ſpiritual, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, celeſtial way of omitting all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which God hath preſcribed, giving God only (if indeed ever) the privat retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and inward actings of the ſoul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40347:57"/> of Word and Sacraments; which is no leſſe then down right profaneneſſe, and (if any worſhip) a will-worſhip of their owne invention for it, never was of divine preſcription. But in ſuch alſo as profeſſe to God and his Altar; I feare we ſhall finde upon ſerious enquiry, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars at leaſt formally, if not materially built beſides the Altars of God: which if any do not diſcerne, I ſhall ſay for their conviction, as <hi>Samuel</hi> to <hi>Saul: What meaneth the bleating of the ſheepe in mine eares, and the lowing of the oxen which I heare?</hi> 1 Sam. 15.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. So ſay I, if we all cleave cloſe to the Altar of God, what meanes the gathering of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in the midſt of us: the diſtinct and oppoſite Aſſemblies: the Church-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant made a dore of admiſſion into Church-memberſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p, even unto the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into one body: the cry of men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Miniſterie as Antichriſtian: and the Aſſemblies of Chriſtians reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as Babyloniſh whores: the loweſt of the people making themſelves Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: with the cry, that <hi>All the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are holy:</hi> and the very oppoſition of Gods owne Ordinances (as to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of them) in the different formes of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40347:58"/> adminiſtration? Do we not ſee ſome dipping in rivers and ſtanding pooles, whileſt others are baptizing in places of publick worſhip: ſome breaking bread in diſtinct ſocieties, ſhutting the doore on ſuch as themſelves cannot deny to be by Baptiſm actually conſecrated Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members (if that be which cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, the doore of admiſſion) but alſo not ejected, nay, themſelves being wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, ſincerely, godly, and ſavingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to Chriſt, though not conforming to their ſeparate conſtitutions, whileſt others adminiſter the Lords Supper to the Lords people as ſuch, though not in ſuch a Church-way? nay, my brethren, may not we ſee principle againſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, preaching againſt preaching, prayer againſt drayer, thankſgiving againſt thankſgiving, and Faſt againſt Faſt? as if we were reſolved to confound the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry God of wiſdome with our divided worſhip of him: in which oppoſition both cannot be the Altar of God, the one muſt needs be our owne threſhold and poſt ſet by Gods threſhold and poſt in the Lords Temple: both cannot plead divine preſcription, and therefore the one muſt needs be humane invention
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40347:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſuperſtition, whatever cry of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſanctity go before it, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company it: now, which of theſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent adminiſtrations are the Altar of God, and which the Altar againſt the Altar of God, I will not determinately pronounce, leſt I be reputed cenſorious, and charged with violence and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the common reproach of ſuch as ſincerely reprove the erroneous princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and practices of our dayes: but to the exciting of the humiliation required, and the quickening of ſincere worſhippers of God to their duty, I ſhall briefly direct to the object by ſome few Characters, the uſual concomitants of Altar-build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that whereſoever we ſee ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitants, we may conclude, or at leaſt be jealous, that they are the people acting the ſinne of Altar-building: and if any mans conſcience ſhall inferre the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from ſuch premiſes rationally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, I deſire them to obſerve the counſel of the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> to <hi>be ſwift to heare, ſlow to ſpeak, ſlow to wrath, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the wrath of man worketh not the righteouſneſſe of God. Wherefore lay apart all filthineſſe and ſuperfluity of maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and receive with meekneſſe the Word
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40347:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> that is graffed in you, which is able to ſave the ſoule,</hi> James 1.19, 20, 21. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the obſervation of a Reverend Expoſitor on the text,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Mant.</hi> on <hi>James</hi> 1 Caracter.</note> the worſt thing we can bring to a religious controverſie, is anger: the firſt character of Altars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Altar of God is, <hi>doctrines diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the truth of God:</hi> for principles muſt needs ſquare the practice and Altar-building muſt needs be theoretical be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be practical: hence commonly called our owne inventions and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations ſo denominated from the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted underſtanding acting the ſame: The firſt prophane Altar that ever <hi>Iſrael</hi> are noted to provoke divine wrath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, was erected with the diſſonant do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>Theſe are thy gods, O Iſrael, that brought thee out of Egypt,</hi> Exod. 32.4. And throughout the whole Hiſtory of the Altar-building of the backſliding Jewes we ſhall finde when ever the Prieſts offered unto <hi>Baal, the Prophets did propheſie lies in the Lords Name:</hi> If they do but formally build Altars, inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Prieſthood, and corrupting the adminiſtration of divine worſhip, it muſt be uſhered in with the doctrine of the peoples holineſſe, and <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aarons</hi>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:40347:59"/> ambition, as did <hi>Corah</hi> and his company under the Goſpel; this ſinne is general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denominated <hi>mans doctrine, another goſpel, the bringing in of damnable doctrine, divers and ſtrange doctrines,</hi> by which ſuch as follow them are ſaid to be perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and turned aſide from the Goſpel &amp; doctrine of Chriſt: and this is obſervable, that the Apoſtle dehorting from divers ſtrange doctrines, enforceth his dehorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with this reaſon, <hi>We have an Alter, &amp;c.</hi> Heb. 13.9, 10. As if he would have ſaid, Theſe divers and ſtrange doctrines are Altars againſt that Altar we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and owned: and when the Fathers (as was before noted) ſaid of Hereticks, that they built Altar againſt Altar, it was occaſioned by their curſed doctrines; ſo that where we ſee any with <hi>Arminius</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance mans free will againſt Gods free grace; or with <hi>Socinus</hi> teach our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to be Gods acquittance againſt the propitiatory ſatisfying (to divine juſtice) property of the blood of Chriſt: With the <hi>Familiſts, Seekers,</hi> or <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> to teach immediate Inſpirations and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of a pretended ſpirit, to be equal to, nay, above the authority of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: With the <hi>Arians,</hi> to deny Chriſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:40347:60"/> his divine nature: With the <hi>Seekers</hi> to deny Goſpel-Ordinances in the matter, or with <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in the manner of their adminiſtration: With the <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> to teach that pollutions are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ground of ſeparation from true Churches, though retaining fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals: that Baptiſme is not ſufficient to admiſſion to Church-memberſhip with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Congregational Covenant; that the holineſſe of men, as Saints, meerely Saints, is a ſufficient authority to invade the Miniſterial function, and the like; there we may ſee, and with ſorrow ſay, Altars are in building againſt the Altars of God: for theſe principles being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the rules of the Lords wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, muſt needs lead to practices oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to his preſcribed performances: this Character is ſo commonly the concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant of Altar-building, that many times the profeſſors of this ſinne conceale from their diſciples the abſurdeſt of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, till by ſome of leſſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they are made <hi>Skepticks</hi> in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo capable of admitting any do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines: and when they dictate any, it is only as preſent light, which they may op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſhortly: as much as may be decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:40347:60"/> the teſte and trial of the Word, that they may be uſually and well called (by the epithete <hi>Tertullian</hi> gave them) <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugae Scripturarum,</hi> ſhunners of Scriptures light.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Character of Altar-build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as many times it's concomitant,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Charact.</hi>
               </note> and indeed cauſe, tis the <hi>publike exhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Aſtrological predictions,</hi> a religion amongſt the Heathen, whoſe Altars ſtand oppoſite to the Altar of God; and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be received as an Art among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and profeſſed people of God, but could never finde entertainment but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the defection from Gods true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and the erection of Idolatry and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition: Starrie prophecies were ever more ſuitable for <hi>Egyptian</hi> and <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> idolaters then <hi>Iſrael</hi>-worſhippers at Gods Altars: never ſhall we read the ſame acted or allowed in <hi>Iſrael</hi> but in Altar-building dayes, and by Altar-build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Princes; and as it roſe with this ſinne, it fell with the ſame, being both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther removed by religious Altar-reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Princes: and uſually the Prophets of God were found in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the place of Gods Altar whileſt Soothſayers and falſe Diviners were in <hi>Samaria</hi> the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar-building
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:40347:61"/> Citie: the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> joynes <hi>Iacobs</hi> being full <hi>with the manners of the Eaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deute. 18.10, 11, 12. Iſa. 44.25.57.12, 13, 14</note> 
               <hi>and Sorcerers of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines:</hi> with their being <hi>full of Idols,</hi> as the cauſes of Gods deſertion of them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.6. Not to ſtand upon the ſeveral upbraiding expoſtulations of God with his owne people and other Nations for attending to the divined lies of their Magicians, Soothſayers, Star gazers, and monethly Prognoſt cators: I ſhall only deſire you to obſerve that which ſeemes a very obſervable evidence of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant Character <hi>(viz)</hi> Gods promiſe in the reſtoration of his Church by Chriſt to cut off <hi>Enchanters,</hi> and that they ſhould have no more <hi>Soothſayers:</hi> is joyned with the reforming of his owne Altar by <hi>cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off their Idols</hi> and turning them from worſhipping the work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their owne hands, <hi>Mic</hi> 5.12, 13. Not only under the Law was this found to be a concomitant (if I may not ſay cauſe) of the many Altars againſt God, but alſo under the Goſpel Soothſaying, Starrie Prediction, Aſtrological Prophecies will appeare an attendant on, or indeed rather a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and precu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſor of Errors, Hereſies, Schiſmes, and ſaddeſt corruptions in the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:40347:61"/> doctrine and worſhip of God that Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Altar at which we worſhip: a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hereof may be the Jewes, who in their blindneſſe retaining <hi>Moſes</hi> againſt Chriſt, are by the Apoſtle hinted to be oppoſite to the Altar of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.13. Do not the dictates of their Starre-numbring Cabaliſts obdurate them in their ſuperſtitious way? Their falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſometimes heighten their hopes of the approach of their fantaſtical Meſſiah (as did <hi>Abraham</hi> the Jew, aſſuring them that the time of his coming ſhould be in 1464.) to the hardening their of hearts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the true Meſſiah already come: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which we may adde the experiences of the Primitive Church in the Hereticks that roſe up to corrupt the Word of truth: if we conſider thoſe ſorts of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, <hi>(viz.) Simonianiſts, Cleobianiſts, Doſitheans, Gortheans, Menandraniſts, Carpocratians, Marcioniſts, Valentinians, Baſilidians</hi> and <hi>Saturnilians</hi>) in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times noted to bring in the falſe Chriſts, falſe Prophets, falſe Apoſtles, renting aſunder the Church with their falſe doctrine againſt God and Chriſt; which <hi>Thebulis</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> received and began to propagate.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb.</hi> Eccl. hiſt. l. 4. c. 21.</note> What a line of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:40347:62"/> Aſtrology may be ſeene in their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, attributing the production of many and various things, to many and various powers: advancing their owne divinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons above Scripture-Divinity: and their Magical practices and enumerations to the aſtoniſhing of their auditors; nay, this line is not only to be ſeene in, but as it were to lead unto their corrupting principles and practice.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb.</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. hiſt. lib. 4. c. 21. <hi>Socra.</hi> Sch. lib. 1. c. 27. <hi>Euſeb.</hi> in Eccleſ. hiſt. lib. 4. c, 11.</note> We might here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto adde <hi>Manes,</hi> the author of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichees,</hi> the founder of the Hereſie of two beginnings, who taught the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of the Sunne, and the like princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, properly flowing from ſtarrie divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and <hi>Marke</hi> the knowne Magician, confuted by <hi>Jrenaeus,</hi> who baptized <hi>in the name of the unknowne father of all things, and in the truth mother of all things, &amp;c.</hi> A clear Altar againſt Gods Altar. But to what purpoſe ſhould we ſend ſo farre to finde Hereſie attended with Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cromancie, when nearer home in later years it hath beene, and is the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to advance the Mahumetan and Popiſh ſuperſtition? who knowes any thing of the Papal ſtories, that knowes not this to have beene the ſtep to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the man of ſin, and that Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:40347:62"/> concluſions, ſtarrie predictions, and magical actions have not only beene countenanced and allowed, but alſo ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died and advanced in their order of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes: To the further evidencing its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence in the Church; we might muſter up the cenſures of free Councels and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Aſſemblies: the condemnations of it by the Primitive Fathers: the wholeſome Lawes, Imperial, Civil, Eccleſiaſtical a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Diviners, Aſtrologers, and the like: the variety of puniſhments, as baniſhment, impriſonment, confiſcation, death to the profeſſors, or indulgers of ſtarrie predictions, and confeſſions of ſome of their owne profeſſors: all which do not only evidence its exiſtence in, but alſo danger to the Chriſtian Churches in the fulneſſe of what is reported to have beene confeſſed by one <hi>Cornelius Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa,</hi> once an Arch-Magician, who bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his miſ-ſpent youth in this Art, ſaith, <hi>They that profeſſe to it, feare not to teach moſt pernicious Hereſies and Infidelities: whileſt they profeſſe with impious temerity, that the gift of Prophecie, the power of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, the ſecrets of conſcience, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over Devils, the vertue of miracles, the efficacie of ſupplications, and the ſtate
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40347:63"/> of the life to come, do all depend on the Starres are vouchſafed by them, and may be knowne by them.</hi> But thus much may be ſufficient to evidence its concommi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancie with this ſin of Altar-building, both before and ſince Chriſt came in the fleſh, and to give us cauſe, if we finde the ſame to ſhew it ſelfe in the mideſt of us (as it uſually puts up in troubleſome times and places, as moſt ſuitable to their doubtful deſtinies) to ſuſpect Altar-building to attend it: but upon ſerious ſearch, and diligent obſervation we ſhall eaſily ſee to the ſadning of pious ſpirits, not only hath Aſtrology appeared under our confuſions and commotions, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo not been rebuked, but rather indulged and countenanced, I, and by too many received to the emboldening of its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors with wonted impudency to enter the liſts, and engage the conteſts for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vining, predicting Aſtrology, ſo often foyled by Civil and Eccleſiaſtical cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in the Church; nay, and by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens themſelves, ſtrangers to the Church: their raging arguments produced againſt arguments of reaſon and Scripture: the reviling tearmes againſt Divines and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, not only now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:40347:63"/> to defend divine providence from their ſtarrie encroachments, but even ſuch as are long ſince rotted in the grave, doing what in them is, to the killing of their labours, which do live, and will live to their conviction and confuſion: their declared enmity to Religion, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing and predicting as the pretended influence of the Starres, the variety of confuſions and ſad diviſions concerning it: evermore propheſying evil to the Truth according to the wonted practice of its profeſſors: and their blazing forth the leaſt of failings; (nay, ſometimes imagined) in Divines, to the rendring of their perſons and function vile: whileſt they ſound the trumpet of their owne praiſe, often recollecting thoſe things they have ſeemingly foretold, and have accidentally come to paſſe, but burying in oblivion their never accompliſhed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions (which may ſet <hi>Mercury</hi> on) work, as <hi>Seneca</hi> once wittily fancied, to intreat the gods to abridge the life of <hi>Claudius,</hi> if for no other cauſe, yet of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pitie and compaſſion to the poore A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers,<note place="margin">as the great Plague threatened to be in <hi>London</hi> 1652.</note> who had already beene taken with ſo many lies from year to year, that if the deſtinies were not more favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:40347:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> then their ground was, ſure the credit of Aſtrology would decay for ever:) of which, if a man ſhould, as it is reported of the Lord of <hi>Arundel,</hi> note but their yearly <hi>Almanacks</hi> with repugnant notes at the beginning, they would oftentimes prove more true then ſuch predictions. Theſe things I ſay are not to be paſt without obſervation as the evidence of that height of their exiſtence and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance in the mideſt of us (which may create our jealouſie, if I may not ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude) the ſin of Altar-building to be on foot among us: Aſtrological impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the peoples faith, lately ſtarted up with peremptorineſſe and impudence; with the peoples apt reception thereof, as more infallible Prognoſtications of the government of the world and Church then either Scripture-prophecie or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe provoked a reverend Divine to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme time from his more ſerious ſtudies to the poſing and puzling of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal-Aſtrological-Diviner:<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>John Gaule</hi> his Magaſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancer, poſed and puzled: ſee his Epiſt. to the Reader</note> induced by this very reaſon, conſcience of duty (to uſe his owne words) to ſtand up, <hi>to ſpeak a word for God, Chriſt, the holy Ghoſt, Church and Saints against a preſſe and peſt of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical, magephemerical, magnaſtrological,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:40347:64"/> &amp;c. of books of late crept, nay, crouded in amongſt us, to the diſhonour of God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of Chriſt, deſpighting the Spirit, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponizing of the Word, diſturbing the Church, ſubverting of Religion, diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the State, ſcandalizing weak Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and ſeducing of common people, yea, to the promotion of Idolatry, Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſme, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee then, my brethren, this ſinful Art of Starre-divining, as a concomitant of the ſin after which we are enquiring, to be too evident in the mideſt of us: I ſhall a little, and very briefly note to you the fitneſſe of this ſinful Art, to chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cterize the ſin of Altar-building, that to the quickening of your affections, you may more ſeriouſly heed it, though it hath beene but ſeldome hinted: and that in noting its nature, and the Churches ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation concerning it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as for its nature: not to ſtand upon it as erroneous, and heretical as it is in it ſelfe, the rules of it, and inferences from the ſame became directly contrary to the doctrine of faith: not its aptitude to engage needleſſe ſcrupuloſities and ſuperſtitious obſervations of this as omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, and that as lucky, to the enſlaving
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:40347:65"/> a mans will in every action to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of every circumſtance, and ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Starres: nor yet of its uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, whereby the event ſometimes falls contrary to the prediction, as <hi>Firminus,</hi> a friend to Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> found in obſervation of the fate of two children borne in his houſe, at one and the ſame moment, which yet was calculated by the ſtarres to be the ſame, but by the Law and cuſtome of the Countrey pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved quite contrary: I ſhall only note its nature in relation to this ſin; and we ſhall finde it of a ſuitable nature to receive and propagate innovations and falſe will-worſhip, not only as it is <hi>Skeptical,</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in nothing but the uncertainty of their owne aſſertions: but alſo as it <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſeth the Stars and Celeſtial bodies into the chaire of divine providence,</hi> whileſt, as was before noted, it placeth all, even ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets and ſupreme happineſſe in the power of the Planets, which doctrine muſt needs ſet them as objects of admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo of adoration: a very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral way to build Altars objectively, by giving the worſhip and honour of the Creator and diſpoſer of all things to the creatures: without doubt this was to the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:40347:65"/> Jewes as to other Nations, the leading principle to worſhip the Queene and the hoaſt of Heaven, nay, further, <hi>dictates a doctrine of univerſal Toleration of all religions:</hi> never in the leaſt admitting any limitation or reſtraint which might be of too ſad a reflection upon it ſelf: Hence <hi>Ptolomy</hi> ſaith, that the diſpoſition or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination which divers Countries have to worſhip one God before another, cometh from the conſtellation of the Planets: as <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturne</hi> make a Jew: <hi>Mars</hi> a <hi>Perſian</hi> to worſhip the fire; <hi>Mercury</hi> a <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> and with the <hi>Moon</hi> an <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> ſo that whileſt this ſinful Prognoſticating Art makes the Planets the authors, it muſt needs make them indulgers and approvers of the exerciſe of all religions, or religious formes, though never ſo repugnant and inconſiſtent each to other: (this is ſure the reaſon why Aſtrologers have in our late dayes Prognoſticated very often the liberty of all religions to be exerciſed, and no Diſcipline for the reſtraint there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ever ſpoken for by them:) and is a fit foundation to build many Altars upon, as obſerved experience hath too clearly evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced, for as an every dayes Sabbath
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:40347:66"/> is no Sabbath, ſo an every way of worſhip without confinement to divine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription is no way of true worſhip un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; for novelty will be building when at liberty: And Aſtrology it ſelfe may by this meanes come to be an Altar, a religion as it was among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, <hi>it's enmity to Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> which nature muſt needs render it very capable of introducing another, though directly oppoſite: this enmity is evidenced by that <hi>antitheſis</hi> it hath ever ſtood in to Religion by the Magical ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, and planitary predicters, notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous malice and envie in defaming, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracing, calumniating, deriding, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning, oppoſing the Miniſters of the Goſpel: and predicting frequently the decayes of the encouragements; nay, and the very falling of their calling, (promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be perpetuated till the Church be perfect in heaven:<note place="margin">Lord <hi>How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> in his Defenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>ch.</hi> 22. <hi>p.</hi> 111.</note>) nay, not only is their enmity againſt the inſtruments, which muſt hold up and continue the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of God, Chriſtian Religion, but by their fatal (yet hitherto falſe) predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt Religion it ſelf; for in the firſt beginning and tender ſpring of faith
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:40347:66"/> the obſervers of the Planets gave out in their Pamphlets, That the Name of Chriſt ſhould not be had in honour at the uttermoſt above two hundred yeares, which falling out by tract of time to be an egregious lie, <hi>Albumazar</hi> (to keep his diſciples in life) adjourned the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Religion two hundred years higher, ſuppoſing undoubtedly this ſhould be the utmoſt ſtint and period of our continuance, which (maugre their malice) continueth to this day, and ſhall continue; ſo that we ſee ſufficient in its nature to make it a character being ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being a cauſe of Altar-building.</p>
            <p>But let us paſſe on to the Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſincere worſhippers of God concerning it: and what wiſe obſerver is or ever hath beene in the Church of God to whom it hath not appeared that thoſe Aſtrological artiſts ever were more rife in Heatheniſh then in Chriſtian, in Popiſh then in Proteſtant, in former then in later times? that they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes moſt buſie in turbulent, diſtracted times and places, where wars domeſtick or forreigne, fitted people for ſedition, faction or ſchiſme, &amp;c. that the proper
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:40347:67"/> fruits of their Schooles, Societies, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Practice, and Profeſſion, were the nouriſhing of Nations in Idolatry, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, Superſtition and Impiety: that men of the greateſt learning, wiſdome, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, conſcience and piety, have not deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and deſpiſed them whileſt men of the contrary diſpoſition have feared their Prognoſtications, and believed their Predictions: but to cloſe up all of much that might be obſerved, that when and whereſoever their Divinations and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſagings were moſt received: it was not a fearful preſage of a decay of Religion, and of a declining Church: in a word, that the Word Church, or true Religion of God never flouriſhed, or was eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in any Kingdome or Nation where Magicians, Diviners, Sooth-ſayers and Aſtrologers were countenanced or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived at; nay, where they were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and ſuppreſſed.</p>
            <p>Now, my brethren, theſe things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, I leave it to every unprejudiced man to conſider whether the acting, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing, ſeeking to, or ſuffering in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, Aſtrology, and its Predictions; give not juſt cauſe to Miniſters of the Goſpel to complaine of, and cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:40347:67" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſuperſtition, innovations, Altar-building againſt Gods Altar, as the ſad attendant on, or effect of Star-gazing? and whereſoever we ſee in divided par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties exerc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſing diſtinct practiſes, this Art to be owned, allowed, pleaded for, and believed; there we may conclude a juſt ſuſpition at the leaſt of their departing from the Lord and his worſhip, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their own inventions.</p>
            <p>The third Character as the conſtant concomitant of Altar-building, is, <hi>dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſeparations from the union of the Saints and body of the Church of God.</hi> This is that which I have before noted to be the ſad effect of this ſin, whether mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially or formally acted, as we have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced in <hi>Corahs</hi> and his company's ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering a Congregation, and diſjoyning themſelves from the Camp of <hi>Iſrael: Jeroboam</hi> and his ſubjects ſeparation from the Temple, not to this day cemented by many evidences and inſtances under the Goſpel. Well may I then call that a concomitant, which was before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved an effect of the ſin, and well may that be a character, which is both a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant and effect of Altar-building: and now (my brethren) I would I could
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:40347:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>I rejoyce to ſee your order and ſtedfaſtneſſe in the faith:</hi> your order in orderly union, every member keeping its proper place without ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or murmuration, and all keeping cloſe in that one body into which we were all baptized, but alas! <hi>(horreſco re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferens)</hi> I ſpeak it to our ſhame and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row this day in the ſight of God, What man that can but halfe ſee, ſeeth not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, ſchiſmes, and ſad diviſions to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in the mideſt of us? ſome men not only profeſſing to this Miniſter, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him up, not only above, but againſt other Miniſters; and others owning that, and adhering to him and his princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, making them matters of faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſpoken by him, rather then ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Word: ſo that <hi>ſome are of Paul, ſome of Apollo,</hi> as if neither them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor the Miniſters were of Chriſt: theſe contentions, ſtrifes, diviſions, the Apoſtle doth not only not commend whileſt he dehorts from ſuch diſſenſions, but expreſſely condemnes them as <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal:</hi> and ſeemees to hint the ſame to be a ſetting of them as objects of their faith, worſhip, and ſo Altars againſt Chriſt the true Altar of them all: whileſt he expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulates,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:40347:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Is Christ divided? was Paul cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for you?</hi> either were ye baptized into the name of <hi>Paul?</hi> rejoycing he had baptized few among them, leſt they ſhould ſay he baptized in his owne name: which expoſtulations are vehement affirmations, that ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominate themſelves by the name of their Teachers, as having their perſons in admiration, though never ſo eminent;<note place="margin">Cujus nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one cenſeri volumus ab eo rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptos ejuſque nos proprios eſse profitemur, baptiſmus eſt ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum confoedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis cum eo in cujus nomen ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptizamur. <hi>Par. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to divide Christ,</hi> to owne their Teachers, <hi>as their Saviours and Redeemers,</hi> and ſuch into whoſe name and profeſſion they were baptized, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13, 14. not only are we (I ſay) thus divided in our profeſſion of relations to this and to that Miniſter: but alſo in Church-way, ſome of Independent Church-wayes, ſome of Arminian, ſome of Socinian, ſome of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſtical, ſome of Seekers, and it were well if ſome were not profeſſedly of ranting Churches and Aſſemblies; all which ſeparate from the body of the Church, refuſing to worſhip God with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in way of miniſtration by him preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, by it practized: and ſuch as do ſo divide, never yet diſproved the ſame, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in matter or forme, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their calumniating charges of all <hi>out
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:40347:69"/> of their way,</hi> though baptized, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved pious, as in wayes and hedges with the Heathen: as the members of the ſcarlet-coloured whore: brats of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> ſubjected to Antichriſtian Miniſtery, out of the way of Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be gathered into a Church way: and exchange their baptiſmal admiſſion into the Church for an admiſſion by a Congregational Covenant; a word: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the faith which is not in them; and engaging to joyne in ſuch Aſſemblies, and be edified in their principles of new light, though never ſo contrary to the old light of Scriptures; nay, and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, and ſo ſubject unto changes: nay, let the ſeveral ſubdiviſions, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing of members from collected ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate Churches: the many Sects and ſorts of Churches that have appeared and beene profeſſed ſince the firſt rent from the body of the Churches in the Nation by the old Browniſts, and of late Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, be a witneſſe of this ſad effect and concomitant which ſo clearly chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cterizing the ſin (whileſt, as I before no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, all of theſe Sects and ſorts that thus ſeparate themſelves from the Church, cannot be all, or any of them the way of
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:40347:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> Gods worſhip, who is one, and will be worſhipped by his owne way, in his own Church.) may irritate our jealouſie, may as premiſes lead us clearly to infer the concluſion that Altars are built, and in building againſt the Altar of God, with which our heart is to be affected, and our ſelves humbled before God, as becomes ſincere worſhippers at his Altar.</p>
            <p>The fourth Character found to be the conſtant concomitant of building Altars againſt the Altars of God, <hi>is deadly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Miniſters of God which wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Gods Altar.</hi> In all Religions, the Prieſt, or Prieſtly Office, (as eſſential to the ſupport of the Altar-worſhip) is ever advanced, protected, and provided for by the friends, ſupplanted, oppoſed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the enemies of ſuch Altar-worſhip: and it is to me very obſervable, that Gods charge of conſtant waiting at his Altar, goes not without a <hi>Take heed thou forſake not the Levite all thy dayes, Deut.</hi> 12 19. So that Altar-Miniſtery, and the Altar it ſelf, whether true or falſe, do alwayes ſtand together: what rebellious innovation read we in the ſtory of Altar-building <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:40347:70"/> with a reſiſtance of the Miniſtery ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to wait at Gods Altar: the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of <hi>Corah</hi> and his company char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth <hi>Aaron</hi> as well as, nay, more immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately then <hi>Moſes, to have taken too much upon him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 11.13, 14.</note> the unjuſt affectation of the Prieſthood is eminently reproved by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and confuted by the miraculous budding of <hi>Aarons</hi> rod: and their Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers beaten into plates: <hi>Jeroboam</hi> ſets not up falſe Altars at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel</hi> without ſuſpending the Miniſters of Gods Altar <hi>ab officio &amp; beneficio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 31.4. 1 Kings 18.19.</note> from their work and wages, and the ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of his hand againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of God ſent from <hi>Jeruſalem: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habs</hi> Altars and Idolatry is not acted without an <hi>Elijah's</hi> complaint,<note place="margin">2 Kings 10 2 Chron.</note> 
               <hi>They have broken downe thine Altars, and ſlaine thy Prophets:</hi> and if ever falſe Altars are ſubverted, and the Altar of God reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, if but by the ſeeming zeale of <hi>Jehu,</hi> or the ſincere zeale of <hi>Elias,</hi> the Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> muſt be the ſacrifice, that the Prieſts of God may be reſtored.<note place="margin">29.13.4 15.3.</note> It is record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the everlaſting honour (and to the luſtre of the reformation) of <hi>Aſa, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> and <hi>Joſiah,</hi> reſtorers of Gods true Altar, that they ſet the Prieſts and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:40347:70"/> (Miniſters of the Altar) in their places, and provided their full mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to their encouragement; putting a period to the ſad complaint that <hi>Iſrael</hi> had now for a long ſeaſon <hi>beene without the true God, and without a Prieſt to teach, and without Law;</hi> not only do inſtances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound thus under the Law, (which we uſe the more, becauſe of the proper uſe of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars under it) but alſo under the Goſpel. Is it not clear to every reaſonable obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant eye; that the Jewiſh and Paganiſh Prieſts oppoſed by themſelves, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked others againſt the Apoſtles of Chriſt? Do not the Apoſtolical Epiſtles demonſtrate the deadly enmity of the falſe Apoſtles againſt the true Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, calumniating them, ſubverting their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, and diſſwading from their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; neceſſitating their boaſting beyond their purpoſe: and pleading in the defence of Miniſterial mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as by the Altar-rule it was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when themſelves had ſufficient and abounded? Did not the rage of Paganiſh perſecution purſue an <hi>Ignatius</hi> or <hi>Policar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> and ſuch Miniſters of the Churches as the principal objects? will not an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate <hi>Julian</hi> ſubtilly labour to ſubvert
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:40347:71"/> the worſhip of Chriſt, by ſubſtracting the Miniſterial maintenance: ſubverting the Schooles of their qualification, and by univerſal toleration, ſupplanting their Ordination of Miniſters. If ever <hi>Arrius</hi> will build his Altar of denying Chriſt his Divinity, <hi>Athanaſius</hi> muſt be the obj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct of his oppoſition: ſo on the other hand, if a Chriſtian <hi>Constantine</hi> will owne and advance the Altar and worſhip of God in Chriſt, he will court and comfort, che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and ſupport the deſpiſed and deject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Miniſters thereof; largely allowing of himſelfe, and providing for their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence and encouragement: for ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticious ſeducers, and will-worſhip-inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators know the Miniſters of the Goſpel to be like the Dog in the Fable, defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſheep from diſſipation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction by their wolviſh property: and the ſincere worſhippers of God well know that God will not be enjoyed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, having appointed a <hi>Moſes</hi> a Mediatour, nor can we expect the tender of divine worſh p in his immediate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, who hath appointed an Ordinance of intercourſe betweene himſelfe and his Church; <hi>the Ministery of his Altar,</hi> which he hath promiſed to vindicate and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:40347:71" rendition="simple:additions"/> preſerve to the end of the world: when ever he promiſed the communications of himſelf to, or the acceptation of worſhip from his Church: ſo that enquiring after the actors of this ſin of Altar-building, we muſt obſerve who they are that expreſs en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mity, not to the perſons of particular Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters only, but to the Miniſtery of Gods Altar, making it a ſufficient guilt, <hi>odium,</hi> and object of enmity to be denominated a Miniſter; let us take notice who decline and deſpiſe it; Who <hi>are they</hi> that make this Office the object of railing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling, denominating it Antichriſtian, needleſſe, imperious, proud, inſulting, enſlaving men to needleſſe nicity, and cruel bondage, and all becauſe it corrects their errour, curbs their ſuperſtition, and commands in the Name of the Lord their obedience to divine preſcriptions: who they are that raiſe perſecution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and with railing tearmes render Miniſters as Miniſters vile in the eyes of men; and by pretended revelations and prophecie decry the Office, ſaying, This Antichriſtian Order and its Ordination to this Office muſt meet with a period: proclaiming liberty to Chriſtians as Chriſtians to invade this Sacred Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:40347:72" rendition="simple:additions"/> and to ſpeak in the Name of the Lord uncalled, and unqualified, and that provoke by principles, petition, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended example to deſtroy and have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the maintenance of ſuch as wait on the Altar, deſigned to them both by God and man: theſe, I ſay, that thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear deadly enemies to the Inſtrument of divine worſhip, the Ordinance of waiting at Gods true Altar, the Goſpel-Miniſtery, although with ſeeming ſanctity, and a ſhout of ſaintſhip, cannot be excuſed from juſt ground (of ſuſpition at the leaſt) of building Altars beſides the Altar of God.</p>
            <p>The fifth Character as the concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant of building Altars beſides the Altar of God, is, <hi>the diſpenſation of divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, without the divine ſtamp of a due Call and Ordination:</hi> God never yet appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Altar-worſhip without an Altar-of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which might not be common to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one, nay, which no man muſt take upon him, but he which is called of God, as was <hi>Aaron.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5.4.</note> If Miniſtery be as (it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied) a diſtinct Office under Law or Goſpel, it muſt needs have a due Inauguration thereunto; for as in a State an every mans Magiſtracie is a no Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie;
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:40347:72" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo in the Church an every mans Miniſtery is no Miniſtery: a ſinful ſeeking of the Prieſts Office, upon the pretence of the peoples holineſſe, to be witneſſed againſt by the plates of their cenſers, and the budding of <hi>Aarons</hi> rod is ſuitable to <hi>Corahs</hi> ſeparate rebellion: a <hi>Whoſoever will, let him bring a bullock, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate himſelf a Prieſt,</hi> is a fit Canon of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboams</hi> conſtituted Altar-worſhip at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel:</hi> the high-way to bring the loweſt of the people into the Prieſts Office. When did falſe Prophets run ſo faſt unſent by the Lord, but when the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were increaſed like the ſtreets in <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> Not to multiply needles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in this clear caſe, let the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Churches of God in al ages wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the uſurpation of the Miniſterial Function never to be found in the Church whileſt the doctrine and worſhip of Chriſt was preſerved pure and uncorrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and never out of the Church when and where falſe doctrines and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous innovations did abound: the promiſe of Chriſt concerning the reſtoring of his Altar and worſhip came not without a promiſe to vindicate this Office from the invaſion of the uncalled trades-man
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:40347:73" rendition="simple:additions"/> to the ſhameful conviction which ſhall extract his owne confeſſion: <hi>I am no Prophet, I am an husbandman men taught me to keep cattel from my youth,</hi> Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch. 13.5. If therefore we would finde who they are that ſinfully build Altars, we muſt conſider who they are that preach and practiſe miniſterial diſcharges with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due Ordination; who they are that countenance and contend for this uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, counting it a glorious liberty that every man may lay his hand on his own head, and ſpeak in the Name of the Lord: were the Lord as eminent and immediate in his vindicative ſtroaks for this ſin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.8</note> as under the Law, how many <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzahs</hi> would be found dead for their uncalled ſetting hand to hold the Ark of Gods worſhip, notwithſtanding the pretence of neceſſity: How many <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi>-like leprous foreheads would be found amongſt us,<note place="margin">2 Chr. 26.17, 18, 19.</note> of ſuch that by at leaſt eighty Miniſters of the Lord have beene warned; it is not for them, but for the Miniſters of the Goſpel to offer unto the Lord. But I ſhall conclude this Character as a juſt cauſe to irritate our humiliation before the Lord with that obſervation of reverend Doctor
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:40347:73" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Hall</hi> upon a caſe not much unlike this, though ſomething different: It is a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the ſervice of God to decline from his owne inſtitutions; we have to do with a power which is wiſe to preſcribe his owne worſhip (in matter and forme) juſt to require what he hath preſcribed, and powerful to revenge what he hath required.</p>
            <p>The ſixth and laſt Character which I ſhall note to you,<note place="margin">Blow at the root <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 8. p. 157.</note> and I will but briefly note it, is <hi>doleful conteſts for univerſal Tolerotion of all religions,</hi> which (a wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e obſervant) notes is nothing elſe but the putting of the true Religion out of all protection, whileſt therein Satan labours to exempt, priviledge, and for ever to ſecure his Agents and Brokers (the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries and Teachers of ſoul-murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doctrines) from being moleſted, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and diſturbed in his work by any Government and Diſcipline Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical or Civil; whereby the hands of all in power are bound up (or rather cut quite off) that they may never be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſerve God as they ought in the protection and propagation of his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel and worſhip: who ſeriouſly conſiders the ſtrict Lawes the Lord left the Jewes
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:40347:74" rendition="simple:additions"/> for the keeping of them to his true Altar, and ſees not univerſal liberty leading from the ſame, to be ſinful: nay, who conſiders mans novellous nature, and ſees not a neceſſity of being kept to ſome one Religion by authority, knowing men are naturally bent to mint Gods ſervices in their owne braine, and to go a whoring after their owne inventions, to the building of Altars beſide the Altar of God: Was this ſinne ever acted in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> where the ſword was ſharp and ſevere againſt innovations? The ſame may be demanded concerning the Chriſtian Churches, and upon the contrary, was not this impiety evermore the effect of impunity and univerſal liberty?</p>
            <p>I have done with the firſt part of the enquiry, whether in the mideſt of us Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars may not be ſeene beſides the Altar of God? which we have too much cauſe to conclude in the affirmative: I have alſo noted the concomitants as Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of this ſin, ſo that the ſubjects <hi>of dangerous doctrine: of divining predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: of dangerous ſeparations: of deadly enmity to Goſpel-Altar-Miniſtery: of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſing divine worſhip without due call: and of doleful conteſts of Toleration of all
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:40347:74"/> religions;</hi> may juſtly be more then ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected abettors, advancers, if not actors of Altar-building: and who thoſe are, I leave to the obſervation of the wiſe, whoſe eyes are in their head: and paſſe forward to the ſecond matter of enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in order to our humiliation.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing to be enquired, for the defect of which we are to be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the preſence of a God of jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, is, <hi>Whether the ſincere worſhippers have or do according to their duty ſee to this ſinne of Altar-building?</hi> wherein we might enquire after their ſenſible obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of, and affectation with the ſin: their ſeaſonable caution, and ſerious counſel to deſiſtance; their ſpeedy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations of their brethren in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of accidental temptation: and their zealous reſiſtance of the ſin according to their places, which was before noted to be acts of this duty in the religious <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> but inſtead of a ſpirit faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſcharging theſe duties, it were well, if to our griefe, and Gods great diſhonour, ſome that have, and eminently do profeſſe to the worſhip of the true God in truth, and whoſe places more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently engage their priority in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:40347:75"/> and ſeeing to innovation, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition Altarbuilding were not to be ſeene.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſtaid by their ſelf-intereſt from furious driving (with a ſeeming zeale for the Lord of Hoſts) againſt the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars and Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> ſuffering <hi>Jehu</hi>-like, <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel,</hi> and the high places thereof to ſtand unremoved and unrebuked, if not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obſerved as to their ſinful nature, ſo ſoone as the houſe of <hi>Ahab</hi> is ſubverted and themſelvs eſtabliſhed in the high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Kingdome: as if Prelatical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations and ſuperſtitious ceremonies were to be deſtroyed as obſtructors of their honour and high enjoyments, not as of a ſinful nature of humane inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and againſt divine preſcription: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! how many may we fear are ſo blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with golden thrones and great reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, rhat they cannot ſee (or rather will not) and ſo deaſned that they cannot hear the reports of Apoſtaſie, backſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, error, hereſie, and erected in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations, whereby they depart from the Lord to build Altars beſides his Altar.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if they be ſeene and heard,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:40347:75"/> are not ſome that ſhould be covered with ſhame, and ſit in ſorrow for ſo grievous a guilt, and greatly provoking ſin: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing and readily ſolacing themſelves, and with Altar-building <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 32.18</note> ſhouting not for grief, but great joy: counting, and calling it a glorious liberty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: reputing the time of the Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof the glory of Goſpel-dayes, rebuking the rebukers of ſo groſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſſe; nay, and what is worſt of all, with brazen faces, and as given up to ſtrong deluſions, think they do God good ſervice that ſo do: preſſing into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God with ſolemne praiſes, as if God were an object of confuſed ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations:<note place="margin">Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation on the golden Calfe.</note> and direct oppoſite wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips: May we not with ſorrow conſider with Doctor <hi>Hall,</hi> that it is a miſerable thing for Governours to humour people in their ſins, and inſtead of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k ng up the breach, to enlarge it? Do we not know that ſin will take heart by the approbation of the meaneſt looker on? but if authority once ſecond it, it growes impudent.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſome ſeeing the ſinne, and ſaying in their hearts, would it might not be, remaine ſinfully ſilent, not conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:40347:76"/> that the wicked are apt to interpret the ſilence of God himſelf as an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of allowance:<note place="margin">Pſa. 50.22</note> and that he that ſees the wickedneſſe of the wicked when du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called to ſpeak, and warnes not from the ſame,<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.18. Acts 2.26.</note> is chargeable with the guilt of the ſin, and reſponſible for the blood of the ſinner: How farre is this from an Apoſtolical ſpirit, who will ſpeak, though by ſpeaking they create ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies?</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, ſee we not ſome ſpeaking againſt the ſin, yet ſlack in their rebukes, much below the zealous reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Jewes in the text, who mince not the matter, but in down-right termes diſcover the nature of the ſin, and denominate it a rebellion againſt God and us: and dictate the aggravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons therof to render it vile, and not only ſo, but with ſword in hand, and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in heart to reduce them to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, warne their deſiſtance, but how many Superiours are l ke old <hi>Eli</hi> in their rebukes? <hi>It is an evil report that I heare of you, my ſons, do not ſo evil againſt the Lord.</hi> Is it not ſad to ſee in very many families, wives, children, ſervants ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly following innovations and humane
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:40347:76"/> inventions againſt the truth and worſhip of God with the ſilence, or at the beſt but ſlack rebukes of their husbands, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and maſters? whoſe ſovereignty exerciſing its juſt ſeverity, might be an inſtrument of keeping them more cloſe to the Altar that is of divine preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It will be no excuſe in the day of the Lord, for our neglect or coole, luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme diſcharge of our duty, to ſay we looked for God to reduce them into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his owne will, when God hath inveſted us with authority, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to this end: ſince God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe expects this from man, why ſhould man expect it from God? We might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, though God could as eaſily have prevented and redreſſed the Altar at <hi>Horeb</hi> by an immediate hand, yet he ſends <hi>Moſes</hi> downe the Mount to do it, by ſhewing his ſeverity: ſevere expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of anger againſt Altar-building, do very well become and ſuit with the meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with the enquiry, I ſhall leave to your ſerious and ſecond thoughts how to finde out the guilt and ſubjects thereof, only if ſuch guilt be found in the Churches of God in the mideſt of us:
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:40347:77"/> that Altars be built, or in building a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Altar of God, and not regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or ſeene unto: it is to us matter of mourning; and to the exciting your hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, give me leave to ſuggeſt to you two or three conſiderations as ſo many aggravations of this evil ſo vile in its nature, as hath beene evidenced: but as to us will be found thereby much more vile and grievous.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing that may excite our ſorrow is ſuch a motive as is in the ſtory under conſideration: <hi>viz. It is a ſinne committed whileſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od is ſtriking for late iniquity:</hi> Is the iniquity of <hi>Peor,</hi> too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for us from which we are not cleanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this day, although there was a plague in the Congregation of the Lord? <hi>Joſh.</hi> 22.17. What a vile nature have we, that whileſt our wounds are greene for a paſt, to run upon a new rebellion? did not our late dayes abound with ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous innovations, giving cauſe to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſts inſultingly to ſay, we were poſting towards <hi>Rome?</hi> were not many pious people burdened in themſelves to ſee <hi>Surplice-ſervice, Altar-bowing, Eaſtern-worſhip,</hi> and the like, introduced to, and impoſed on the Church as abſolute
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:40347:77"/> parts of divine worſhip? Were not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faithful Miniſters for their non-ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of ſuch will worſhip ſuſpended, ſilenced, and for their zealous reſiſtance many wayes afflicted? Was not the Lord provoked? did not his diſpleaſure ariſe? have we not felt the weight of his ſtroke, and ſmart of his rod? are our wounds yet healed, our deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions repaired, and our glory reſtored? O then may it not be grief and heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit to ſee ſome ſo ſoone to be turned from innovations of ceremonies to the bringing in of innovated do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes, from ſuch as were but circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial, and conſerved the ſubſtance of divine worſhip, to thoſe that are funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, in danger to ſubvert the whole frame of the divine Altar of Goſpel-worſhip? O how ſad is the echo that (methinks) I hear uttered from heaven againſt <hi>England, Why ſhould you be ſmitten any more, ye revolt more and more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that may affect our hearts, and engage our hearty humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before God for the ſin of Altar-building may be this; that if it be found in the mideſt of us unreſiſted, it is <hi>a ſinne
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:40347:78" rendition="simple:additions"/> committed under a ſolemne Covenant,</hi> wherein we ſtand obliged to the Lord, and with chearful hearrs and hands lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up to the moſt high God, have ſworne,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That we ſhall ſincerely, really, and conſtantly, through the grace of God, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour in our places, &amp;c. the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Reformed Religion in the Church of Scotland, &amp;c. And to bring the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of God in the three Kingdomes, to the neareſt conjunction and unifermity in Religion, in Confeſſion of Faith, Forme of Church-government, Directory for worſhip, and Catehizing, &amp;c.</hi> Artic. 1.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>We ſhall in like manner with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſons, endeavour the extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of Popery, Prelacy, &amp;c. Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Hereſie, Schiſme and Prophaneneſſe, and whatſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver ſhall be found contrary to ſound doctrine, and the power of godlineſſe, &amp;c. that the Lord may be one and his Name one in the three Kingdomes.</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. 2.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever is conceived, and hath beene pleaded by ſome for the ceſſation of the obliging power of ſome Articles in this Covenant, yet I keow not any that have denied its obligation, and yet
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:40347:78"/> binding force in theſe Articles, and to theſe duties, unleſſe it be ſuch as profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly jeſting with the whole, have called, or counted it <hi>an Almanack out if date:</hi> whileſt therefore we are under the Oath of God, may we not be covered with ſhame to ſee it broken? Oh, can we with comfort remember our paſt condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Vowes violation, and diſpenſations from the obliging power of Oaths in others, and run our ſelves under the ſame guilt? O perfideous Nation that will keep no promiſe made, though to the God of faithfulneſſe! O perjurious people, whom ſacred bonds cannot binde, nor ſolemne Oath oblige! Can you without bluſhing look upon the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant hanging in the places of Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, it may be many of your names ſubſcribed to it, as an evidence of your ſolemne obligation by it: and remember that whileſt you have ſworne uniformity, you propagate, or at leaſt indulge mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiformity of Religion? whileſt you have ſworne the extirpation of <hi>Baals</hi> Altars, do you countenance or carry on the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtition, Hereſie, Schiſme? whileſt you have ſworne to endeavour that the Lord m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one, and his Name
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:40347:79"/> one: Do you caſt his worſhip accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your wills, and caſt off his owne ſtanding rule, and indulge mens wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping him, and profeſſing his Name according to their corrupt fancies, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be conſcience? think you not God to be a God of jealouſie, that will, and of power that can avenge the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of his Covenant? Againſt what ſin hath his ſeverity beene expreſſed ſo much as thoſe ſins that have beene acted after, and againſt ſolemne Oaths? Let us with ſorrow and ſhame remember that the Lord was wroth with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and put them out of his ſight, becauſe they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook his Statutes and his Covenant: and made Calves, and built Altars unto them contrary to his commandments, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.15, 16, 17. and their obliging oaths.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, we have the more cauſe to be humbled before the Lord, for that <hi>the ſevere judgements of God may ſeize upon us,</hi> and we have cauſe with feare to expect them: I have before noted that Altar-building doth incurre Divine diſpleaſure, and ſubject a people to the fury of the Lord: how may we mourne to ſee the ſin acted and allowed, which
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:40347:79"/> is the ſad <hi>omen</hi> of approaching mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, this may affect our hearts, and fill us with ſorrow, that ſinful Altar-building is <hi>a ſad provoker and ſymptome of the Lords departure;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 6.8.</note> the laſt, but heavieſt of his judgements. God will ſtay and threaten many miſeries before it come to <hi>a leaſt my ſoul depart from you:</hi> I cannot but much obſerve the words of <hi>Phineas</hi> in this ſtory, when the two tribes and halfe vindicated themſelves from the jealouſie of their juſtly ſuſpicious bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren concerning their Altar-building,<note place="margin">Rectè colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gati ſeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m apud Iſraelitas preſentem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſse quia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e igionis conſenſus adhuc ab ipſis colitur <hi>Maſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n loc.</note> 
               <hi>This day I perceive that the Lord is among us, becauſe ye have not done this treſpaſſe, Joſh.</hi> 22.31. which words do clearly imply, that Altar-building againſt Gods Altar, is an undoubted argument, not only of Gods future, but preſent ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: for if by unity and conſent in divine worſhip Gods preſence be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued; by the rule of contraries, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in, and diſſent from divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip muſt needs argue his abſence: <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariorum contraria eſt ratio:</hi> Contrary reaſons enforce contrary aſſertions. O then, my brethren, is it not a woe to us,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:40347:80"/> that God is departed from us, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Gods departure in reſpect of his counſelling, ſin curbing, guiding and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting preſence, is a ſad preſage of his departure in reſpect of his bleſſing, preſerving, protecting preſence: the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall abſence of God is hell it ſelf: then every with-drawing of himſelf muſt be a ſpark of that fire: Happy is the man or place with whom God ſtayes to chide; for whileſt he ſtayes to reprove, there is favour in diſpleaſure; but when he leaves either man or Church, there is no hope but of ſin and vengeance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the withdrawing of divine preſence is notbing elſe but the preſence of his wrath: O can we read the Schiſmes, Errours, Hereſies, and many innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the mideſt of us; thoſe ſad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and ſymptomes of divine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing, as written in moſt legible characters without grief in our hearts, and tears in our eyes; nay, with a loud cry of golden liberty, and glorious times? O let us ſmite upon our thigh, and ſay, What have we done? Let us ſit in the duſt and ſigh: Let us call for the mourning women, that they may lament: conſidering that the moſt
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:40347:80"/> heart-piercing and doleful tune that ever Altar-building <hi>Iſrael</hi> did lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly expreſſe as the very height of their maladies and calamities, was <hi>the Comforter that ſhould relieve my ſoul, is farre from me,</hi> Lam. 1.16.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Uſe that I ſhall make of the Point, is of exhortation unto ſuch as profeſſe (but are ſuſpected in the Church of God) to be ſincere worſhippers of God: and unto them I would in the Name of the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire <hi>to think well of their brethrens jealous enquiry after their courſes, and ſuſpition of their rare and unuſual pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices ſpringing from unknowne princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples:</hi> and with a ſpirit of meekneſſe beare their juſt reproofes and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an cautions, compoſing themſelves to give an account unto their brethrens demands, and readily to declare the grounds and reaſons of their more then ordinary undertakings: I do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but juſt actions may be unjuſtly ſuſpected and condemned to be ſinful: but if this jealouſie can plead igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, it will thereby expect juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion rather then cenſure: animoſity of ſpirit, and outcries of violence and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:40347:81"/> bitterneſſe againſt the modeſt demands of jealouſie doth very much argue guilt: for it is an obſervation as true as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>Innocencie fears no trials.</hi> We ſhall finde an example in this very ſtory worthy imitation, the ten tribes and a half heating of an Altar-building-work, by their Ambaſſadours make a ſevere expoſtulating, reproving de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the ground and end of ſo ſudden, ſtrange, unconſulted, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>declared action: yet we here have no complaints of violence, bitterneſſe, or cenſoriouſneſſe, but a ſpeedy and meek ſubmiſſion to their brethrens demand, readily declaring their motive to this work <hi>(viz.)</hi> to engage poſterity to Gods Altar before the Arke, their end in the erecting this Altar to be, that it may be a witneſſe of their relation to the God of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Where is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of brethren which ſhould engage a ready ſatisfying of the ſuſpitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of brethren? Where is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of due ſubjection to the authority of the Churches, which ſhould declare principles and practices, and ſubmit them with meekneſſe unto triall? If brethren ſtand at diſtance from ſuch
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:40347:81"/> and expreſſed offence againſt their ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar unuſual courſes, may they not reflect upon themſelves, and conclude it to be a ſelf created croſſe, whileſt in pride or peeviſhneſſe they refuſe to declare and ſubmit to cenſure the ground and end of their ſtrange proceedings? Have not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a <hi>Phinehas</hi> both joyntly and ſingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of ſeparating congregational bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, a platforme of their pretended way of Chriſt, a ſum of their ſetled prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to which they would ſtick, without making new light old: an expreſſe of the rules drawn from Scripture, which ſhall regulate their practice and proceedings ſo different from their brethren, if I may not ſay dividing from the body of the Church of God; that they might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the patterne in the Mount, the Scriptures of God, by which all the way of the Churches muſt be judged? O that I might once more intreat in the name of the ſincere worſhippers at Gods Altar, though not ſo immediately delegated as was <hi>Phinehas,</hi> or ſome of the Miniſters of Gods Goſpel-Altar that have demanded it) that they would at laſt (after all their proteſtations, that they would walk cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt with Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt according to Goſpel-rule,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:40347:82"/> and Apoſtolical practice: their ſolemne promiſe to their brethen, the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of which hath been long, though in vaine expected:) approve their brotherly affection, and a due ſubjection to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, by drawing up a plat-forme of the way in which they walk: accommodating their brethren with the principles that rule their practice, ſubmitting the ſame with alacrity, and meekneſſe, unto trial: that an inability or unwillingneſſe to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcover the ſame, ſtirre and ſtrengthen not ſuſpition, and give us cauſe to conclude them <hi>Lucifugae Scripturarum,</hi> decliners of trial. Let me once more note to them this is neceſſary, that their principles may juſtifie or condemne the practice of ſome that have taken up the profeſſion of Chriſt in their way; for if we muſt gather their principles from preſent practice: their gathering Churches out of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: their covenant-admiſſion into Church-memberſhip: their private mens preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and adminiſtration of Sacraments, with the Schiſme they have made from that one body in which they were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed: we cannot but be jealous with a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly jealouſie, that they do at the leaſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:40347:82"/> build Altars againſt the Altar of God.</p>
            <p>The ſecond exhortation which may rather be a dehortation, is unto ſuch as are turned aſide from the holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and do either materially, as the Pap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſts and others; or formally, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational Separatiſts, build Altars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Altar of God: in the Name of the Lord deſiſt your work, ſtay your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, ceaſe to build; for your work will finde no acceptance with the Lord. Shall I uſe to you the dialect in the text, <hi>Rebel not againſt the Lord and againſt us</hi> (your brethren,) <hi>to build you Altars beſide the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tar of the Lord.</hi> Conſider that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Gods patience may long beare, and whileſt you offer Incenſe to the Queene of heaven, and corrupt the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of a holy God, you may have plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of victuals, you may be well, and ſee no evil; yet fury will be provoked, and take away corne, and wine, and oyle, &amp;c. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. Conſider, and lay it ſeriouſly to heart, that offering falſe fire to the true God, and adoring a falſe god, are Homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneal, of the ſame nature, Altars againſt God: God is provoked to jealouſie by the rivality of falſe worſhip, as well as of falſe gods.</p>
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:40347:83"/>
            <p>I ſhall not I hope againe need to open the fury of the Lord provoked by, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed againſt this ſin: only let me in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral note to you, that God hath reſolved to cover Altar-builders with ſhame, and fill them with bluſhing, notwithſtanding his long ſilence he hath reſolved that they ſhall be <hi>aſhamed of their ſtrange ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices,</hi> Hoſ. 4.19. <hi>and of the Oaks which they have made, and the gardens which they have choſen,</hi> Iſa. 1.29. Know, that if any will preſume to ſtep out of his calling, and ſpeak in the Name of the Lord, uncalled; that God hath ſaid, who both can and will ſee it done: <hi>The Prophet ſhall be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med every one of his Viſion;</hi> and in their ſhame ſhall ſay, <hi>I am no Prophet, I am an husbandman; for men taught me to keepe cattel from my youth,</hi> Zech. 13.4. I ceaſe to admire, &amp; cannot but adore the juſt deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a righteous God, that the doctrine &amp; practice of the Nicolaitans was uſually an attendant, or effect of the Hereſies and Innovations of the Primitive times, and that ſinful ſeparations and Altar-build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing innovations in matter or in forme, hath produced indulgence of filthy and abominable Ranting principles and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices in our dayes: when I ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:40347:83"/> that ſad denunciation of this ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful judgement in <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.12, 13, 14. The ſpirit of whoredome hath cauſed to erre, and they have gone a whoring from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their God, they ſacrifice on the tops of the mountains, and burne Incenſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hills under the Oaks, &amp;c. <hi>Therefore your daughters ſhall commit whoredome, and your ſpouſes ſhall commit adultery: I will not puniſh your daughters when they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit whoredome, nor your ſpouſes when they commit adultery: for themſelves are ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated with whores, and they ſacrifice with harlots.</hi> Take heed leſt God ſay unto you, as he once ſaid unto <hi>Ephraim,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they <hi>have multiplied Altars to ſinne, Altars ſhall be unto them to ſin,</hi> Hoſ. 8.11. For pretended piety in the increaſe of Altars may be juſtly puniſhed with obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie in the ſin, that God may ſay, Seeing they will introduce ſinful innovations contrary to divine preſcriptions, they ſhal ſo do to their ſhame and ſin. The Lord perſwade the hearts of ſuch as ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly build Altars in matter or forme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Altar of God, to returne and ſincerely ſpeak the language of repenting <hi>Ephraim, What have I to do any more with Idols?</hi> So, what have we to do any more
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:40347:84"/> with Altars, Innovat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons, humane inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? we will wait on, and follow after divine preſcriptions.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt exhortation is, to ſuch as are ſincerely, and indeed worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of God at his own only Altar, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faſt the Covenant of God walking according to divine commandment, and keeping communion with the Churches of God; them I would exhort in the Name of the Lord <hi>to stick cloſe to the Altar of God, and ſet your ſelves in your ſeveral places againſt ſuch as build Altars againſt Gods Altar:</hi> Let not your ſouls be unſtable in the wayes of the Lord, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining divine preſcriptions, and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing humane inventions, and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous innovations: Let the world witneſſe you to be conformable Non-conformiſts, who not conforming to ſome Canons and Cuſtomes of the Churches, contrary to, and inconſiſtent with the Canon of Scripture, yet readily conforme to the worſhip in matter and forme, compoſed according to the patterne in the mount, the Word of God, conſerving the unity of, and communion with the Churches of God, that continue the Altar according to divine preſcription: ſet your zeale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:40347:84"/> ſuperſtition, ruſhing from extreme to extreme, ſchiſmatical ſocieties, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical principles, and practice; proclaime ſincerity, and not ſchiſme; following af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter purity in divine worſhip, and not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: to have been the cauſe of that non-compliance which expoſed you to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt charge of Puritaniſme, and ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Temple and Altar of God. Oh be perſwaded to ſhake hands with ſuch as ſhake hands with God and his worſhip. If any will cry, the people are all holy, to the decrying of Goſpel-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, conclude them too prophane for you to joyne with. Let not example, or eminent profeſſions of piety perſwade you to receive principles or practices un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved. Be ſure to follow the counſel of God, to go forth by the footſteps of the flocks, and to feed their kids beſide the ſhepherds tents, when you are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to turne aſide by the flocks of Altar-building companions: for unity to, and (as <hi>Diodate</hi> notes) imitation of the true Churches of Chriſt, is a preſervative a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Apoſtaſie to Idolatry. If the ten Tribes would drive to the Altars at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> draw (with the Levites, and all that ſet themſelves to ſeek the Lord)
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:40347:85"/> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to ſacrifice to the Lord at his own Altar: though with the loſſe of your Cities, Suburbs, and ſweet enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: though <hi>Iſrael</hi> play the harlot, let not <hi>Judah</hi> offend; come not to <hi>Gilgal</hi> to tranſgreſſs, nor to <hi>Bethaven</hi> to ſwear by the Lord: put your ſelves in dayes of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Apoſtaſie, to be hid amongſt the thouſands of the Lord that bow not the knee to <hi>Baal:</hi> and under the protection of that God, that can reſtraine the fury of the fire, and rage of roaring Lions, when let looſe againſt his ſervants for their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herencie to his Altar and worſhip; mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt your ſelves approved in the Lords Sanctuary, now Hereſies are abroad, to a diſcovery of the unfound. Will it not be an anſwer of confidence and comfort to the Lords demand in a day of general de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and dolor,<note place="margin">1 Kings 19.10.</note> The children of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el have forſaken thy Covenant broken down thine Altars, and ſlaine thy Prophets, and I, even I only am left alone?</hi> Is not conſtant adherencie to the ſincere worſhip Altar of God commended to us by a cloud of witneſſes, who ſuffered moſt exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the ſame, not only by the Jews and Pagans, profeſſed enemies to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of God; but alſo by the Donatiſts, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatians
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:40347:85"/> and Arrian Heretiques, apoſtatized from the truth of divine worſhip, beſides Papiſts and Germane Anabaptiſts, who baptized ſuch <hi>baptiſmo flaminis</hi> with fire, as would not be according to their fancie baptized <hi>baptiſmo fluminis</hi> with water; ſo that you ſee the counſel of God and cloud of witneſſes in the Church, charging you to take heed of will-worſhip, humane inventions, Altar-building beſide the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of God.</p>
            <p>Not only are you to be exhorted to ſtick cloſe to the Altar of God, and take heed of declining to, or turning after falſe Altars; but alſo <hi>in your places, according to your capacity, ſet your ſelves againſt the ſin of Altar-building,</hi> ſenſibly obſerving, ſadly bewailing, and ſpeedily ſuppreſſing the ſin in ſuch as act, or advance it. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver let it be ſaid that profeſſed worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers at Gods Altar ſhut their eyes at the increaſe of Altars againſt God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſilent under the ſleighting of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine preſcription, and ſinful innovating of ſuperſtitious matter or formes in the Lords ſervice. Sad is the age in which we live; for that Chriſtianity muſt be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by apologizing for, nay, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the defence of univerſal liberty of
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:40347:86"/> all, or any way of divine worſhip: and moderation made to conſiſt in a mincing and extenuating of this ſin of Altar-build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; nay, in a poſitive ſilence as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it: as if <hi>Moſes</hi> heart might not be ſoft towards <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whileſt his fury is hot againſt their Calfe and Altar: or <hi>Paul</hi> let his moderation be known to all men, and yet fervently ejaculate a <hi>Would they were cut off that trouble the Churches</hi> by their Altar-building ſuperſtitious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines. Be not deceived, my brethren, ſins complaint of violence and bitterneſs, muſt be no check to ſincere zeale: what if many things accompany Altar-building which are of the Lords own drawing and directing;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Halls</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the Calfe at <hi>Horeb.</hi>
               </note> may not <hi>Moſes</hi> more hate the golden Calfe wherein is engraven the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> then honour the Tables of ſtone, wherein God had engraven his Commandments, and long more to deface the Idol, then care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Tables? What ſoul knowes the right nature of zeale, and ſubſcribes not to that unqueſtionable truth, that <hi>every man</hi> quoad captum, <hi>in their places, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their powers, are bound to defend the Altar of God againſt all contrary Altars of humane erection?</hi> conſidering the ſword
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:40347:86"/> put into the hand of the Magiſtrate, the cenſures into the power of the Church, not only to be uſed againſt ſins of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, but alſo of the firſt Table: and ſee not ſufficient reaſon to ſet it ſelf againſt (much leſſe to countenance and indulge) ſuch as ſet their poſt by Gods poſt, their threſhold by the Lords thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhold. The general commands of God to deſtroy the Altars and places built againſt his, with the exemplary zeale, not only under the Law, but alſo und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the Goſpel of Civil as well Eccleſiaſtical powers, may be forcible inducements to the reſiſtance and reſtraining of Altars againſt Gods: as of <hi>Conſtantine, Theodoſius, Valentinianus</hi> and others; expreſſely decreeing, that in all places, and throughout every City the Temples be ſhut up, and liberty be denied to wicked men, to have acceſſe thither to commit Idolatry: as alſo that men be reſtrained from making ſacrifice, whereby they reſtrained falſe Altars, though I confeſſe they compelled not to the Altar of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bulling.</hi> 2. Decade 7, and 8. Ser.</note> I ſhall never owne or indulge ſuch Papal cruelty, as did drive with whips the Pagan Natives in <hi>Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> to the font to be baptized before they were catechized in, and convinced of the
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:40347:87"/> doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ferus <hi>in Decla. in</hi> Joſh. <hi>22.</hi> Vtinam ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis zelus in nobis eſſet, &amp; quidem non unum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ltare ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numera.</note> &amp; divine worſhip: yet I wiſh <hi>Ferus</hi> wiſh that men in power in republiques might imitate the Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical zeal of theſe Emperours, in nor on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſtraining Heatheniſh, but alſo Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Heretical Altars, and contending for unanimity in divine worſhip among ſuch as have laid hold on Gods Covenant, &amp; are profeſſed members of the Church: and that the authoritative Aſſemblies of the Churches would follow the foot-ſteps of the Apoſtolical Councel at <hi>Antioch,</hi> againſt the Altar of Circumciſion: the Synods in <hi>Aſia,</hi> at <hi>Ancyra,</hi> at <hi>Antioch,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> held againſt the <hi>Montaniſts</hi> Altar-build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Heretiques, when and where they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated <hi>Montanus:</hi> Synods at <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 246. and 254. againſt <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatus</hi> and his Hereſie: at <hi>Antioch</hi> to the ſuppreſſing and condemning the Hereſie of <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus,</hi> and of the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi> and other Councels againſt the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Hereſie: and alſo the authority that Jeſus Chriſt hath left in his Church to the rejecting of Altar-building Heretiques after the firſt and ſecond admonition: the charge of particular Elders of the Churches is charged on the Elders of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> in them on all others to look to
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:40347:87"/> the Churches of God committed to their charge, that they follow not ſeducers, which may ariſe from among themſelves to draw aſide diſciples after them.</p>
            <p>Let us take heed of adding ſilence or ſinful indulgence of Altar-building (as the more ſad ſymptom of Gods departure) to the too many eminent and too evident ſignes thereof extant in the mideſt of us: what a black but of blemiſh was it to <hi>Aſa, Amaziah,</hi> and other reforming Kings of <hi>Judah, That the high places were not removed, but the people yet did ſacrifice?</hi> Will it not then be regiſtred to all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ages to the infamie of our begun Reformation, that Altar-building was acted by ſome eminent zealots therein, and ſuperſtitious doctrines and practice eminently indulged by univerſal Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? The late liberty of innovating ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and ſuperſtitious ceremonies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the ſubſtance of divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, though unfit to be annexed, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted a poſting towards Popery: but I am ſure, ſuffering, and not ſuppreſſing Schiſmes, all ſorts of doctrines, though never ſo diſſonant to divine dictates, and liberty to embrace any religion without the eſtabliſhing the Lords Altar, is, &amp; will
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:40347:88"/> be found to be the high-way to Atheiſm. The Miniſters of the Goſpel generally throughout the Nation, not many yeares ſince, acted by a ſpirit of zeale, did<note n="*" place="margin">Their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation to the ſolemn <hi>League</hi> &amp; <hi>Covenant,</hi> againſt Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, Sſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmes, and the tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt Schiſme, Errours, Hereſies, and the protection thereof by univerſal Toleration: Oh my brethren, take heed you loſe not your firſt love: be intreated in the fear of the Lord to know the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority with which Chriſt hath inveſted his Churches, and entruſted you to the defending of his Altar, when Magiſtrates will not (nay, it may be there is no Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate for to) do it: unite you together in the fear of the Lord, exhibit and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the Diſcipline of the Lord in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of his people. Let not the bounds of Suſpenſion and excommunication be utterly removed, as if never placed by the Lord about his holy Mount: Let the men of the world ſee that Chriſt can have a Church in a Nation formally no Nation, but a <hi>Chaos</hi> of confuſed people: ſecond your atteſtation with a firſt and ſecond exhortation to Altar-builders, if they will not ceaſe, follow them with rejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and cutting off from the Sanctuary of God. Conſider ſeriouſly, that if the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the Church them that <hi>hold the
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:40347:88" rendition="simple:additions"/> doctrine of Baalam, and of the Nicolai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans:</hi> and <hi>ſuffering the woman Jezabel, which calleth her ſelf a Propheteſſe, to teach and ſeduce the Lords people:</hi> be the few things that God hath againſt us; we ſhall have cauſe to fear that we ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> in their ſad rejection for following them in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Toleration. Let therefore the Prieſts and Princes; nay, all the people of Gods <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſay to ſuch of their brethren, as they ſuſpect to depart from the Lord; nay, and according to their capacity, labour to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it, that they may not rebel againſt the Lord, and againſt us, to build an Altar beſide the Altar of the Lord.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40347:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40347:89"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
